<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Qajaq Rolling</title>
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com" />
    <updated>2023-08-21T10:02:16+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>David Täng</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://qajaqrolling.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>34 Paddling Upside Down</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/34-paddling-upside-down.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/34-paddling-upside-down.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T13:04:26+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This manoeuvre is pretty straight forward. I put my paddle under the qajaq, capsize and go. Now there are a few hint to be able to go far... First of all - go straight! The points awarded are calculated from the straight line and I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2ItkD4_yoTY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>This manoeuvre is pretty straight forward. I put my paddle under the qajaq, capsize and go. Now there are a few hint to be able to go far...</p>
<p>First of all - go straight! The points awarded are calculated from the straight line and I normally have to paddle next to a line in the water with distance markings. If the water is clear it can be possible to see the line and adjust my path to it. I get 1 point for the first 3 meters and 1 additional point for every two meters after that. 5 meters is 2 points, so is 6 meters. </p>
<p>I have seen paddlers rocking the qajaq to get the paddle deeper in the water as in a sprint stroke. That is a good idea both for power and for going straight.</p>
<p>To get a low profile under water is beneficial, lower drag, longer distance. I try to have my nose on the deck but it's hard. Hard to see where I'm going and hard because I compress my lungs. </p>
<p>The most important aspect of this manoeuvre is to hold my breath for a looooong time. I have got some help from free divers. When I practice I rarely measure my distance, more counting the seconds or strokes I make. Counting strokes are easier, seconds have a tendency for me to speed up as I get a bit stressed under water. </p>
<p>Practice paddling upside down! There are a lot of points go gain and it's not very difficult. It can be worth as much as a Straight Jacket Roll... (23 meters = 11 points)</p>
<p>Judges note: The distance is measured along the straight marked line. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>33 Straight Jacket Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2023-08-21T10:02:16+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I have finally made it. With the excellent help and instructions of Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and Jörgen Fagereng Wessel! Thank you! This is an excellent example of how hands on instruction is invaluable to written instructions. I posted the instructions I got from Anne-Sofie and Jörgen&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AnJsrpmyAoU" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></figure>
<p>I have finally made it. With the excellent help and instructions of Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and Jörgen Fagereng Wessel! Thank you! This is an excellent example of how hands on instruction is invaluable to written instructions. I posted the instructions I got from Anne-Sofie and Jörgen earlier this spring but couldn't make out what I really needed to do, well they showed me. </p>
<p>This is what I can tell you about my journey so far.</p>
<p>Prerequisites: <br>A strong will to succeed, the process can be a bit painful at times. <br>A qajaq that fits you, low back deck, full contact with your thighs. <br>Good twist in your torso<br>An understanding of what supports you; water, shoulders, secondary stability, weight distribution inside and out. <br>You should be able to do an Elbow roll with some ease, double elbow as well. If not start there. </p>
<p>Yoga and stretching. YES! For me this is somewhat painful but makes all the difference. And it takes time so don't set a timetable, do what you can and things will come to you. </p>
<p>Qajaq: This is one of the reasons I got into SOF qajaq building, so I can build myself a qajaq which allows me to do a SJ roll. Not that the qajaq does anything for you but some attributes need to be fulfilled. My current one (T2D5 - TvångsTröja David #5 or Strait Jacket David #5) is great, built for this purpose alone. There are two issues with it, the masik is a tad too high and it's black, l loved my brown ones. The R2D4 (Rockhopping and Roll David#4) had a masik slightly lower and I had to push my knees under it, so I raised it 1 cm for T2D5 and now I regret it a bit. When I lean forward my arms touch the masik stopping me from getting low on the foredeck. This isn't a problem in forward finishing rolls since my arms are not in the way but.... <br>Padding and a snug fit is vital for this roll. Both at the masik and at the hips. If your hips slide down in the qajaq to the water gunwhale it's very hard to get past the secondary stability and on to the back deck. I have now padded my hips as much as I can without restricting but/hip movement. </p>
<p>The main things I work on at the moment are:<br>Getting my shoulders flat and parallel to the surface as I reach up towards the sky before I start the backward sweep.</p>
<p>As I get to the static brace position I push my head back and try to keep my shoulders flat. I can now stay in the static brace - straight jacket if my timing is a bit off and I can't recover in one motion. It's clear to me now that timing is important but not crucial.<br><br>To recover to the back deck I need to ease up with my lower back first, then chest and head out of the water last. This is what Anne-Sofie and Jörgen wrote to me and later showed in detail. </p>
<h3>Additional sources: </h3>
<p>I also got this answer from Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and Jörgen Fagereng Wessel on Facebook:</p>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>Straitjacket roll learning process:</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>I assume you already know the hand and elbow rolls.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>I split most back ending rolls in two parts:</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>1) the capsized to balance brace and</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>2) balance brace to back deck.</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>For the straitjacket roll getting the first part is a matter of timing, strong hip/knee drive and sufficient twisting of upper body. The second part is what most people seem to struggle with. If you manage to use the momentum from the first part that is great, but I found that it was easier to simply learn it from balance brace.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>Again, good twist of upper body is important, so is backward flexibility (practice the cobra stance in yoga).</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>I practiced a lot of balance bracing! Then it was beginning to go from balance brace to back deck with hands folded, and repeating while gradually moving the hands closer to the correct straitjacket position. In the beginning I found it helps moving my sea leg over to the other side in the kayak (every bit helps).</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>The kayak matters a lot, so does padding and fitting. I can not do the straitjacket roll in many kayaks, and I have some padding under front of the kayak (like a padded masik) and some at the hips to keep me from slipping too far to one side of the kayak. If it is too tight it limits my movement and twisting.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>It is important to try to use the lower back muscles to try to get the lower back up on the back deck, not just the upper torso and head.</em></div>
</div>
<h3>I found this on Helen Wilsons site <a href="http://www.greenlandorbust.org">www.greenlandorbust.org</a></h3>
<p><em>Often when first attempting the Straitjacket Roll, the paddler tries to “sweep” onto the back deck, and essentially bumps into it. They can hang out there all day (breathing), but not actually get onto the deck. Does this sound familiar? In this description, the “sweep” is the problem. This “sweep” usually works with a hand roll, fist roll, brick roll and sometimes even the Elbow Roll, but it will not work with the Straightjacket Roll. For the Straightjacket Roll, you need to think of your upper body as a lever, and instead of trying to “sweep” onto the back deck, push your upper body toward the ground, which will give you the leverage to fully recover. Following are the steps to a successful Straightjacket Roll (described with a right-side recovery):</em></p>
<p><em>– Place your arms against your chest with your fingers and thumbs under your armpits.</em></p>
<p><em>– Capsize to the left with your shoulders parallel to the side of the kayak and your forehead down (this will give you a rounded spine).</em></p>
<p><em>– RELAX until your body gets to the highest position possible on the right side of the kayak (your shoulders should be parallel to the surface).</em></p>
<p><em>– Throw your upper body toward the ground, using your back as a lever and keeping your shoulders parallel to the surface. Simultaneously, drive hard with the right knee.</em></p>
<p><em>– Slide up onto the back deck (your head may hit the side of the kayak during the recovery).</em></p>
<p><em>– Helen</em></p>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">Two pros giving their thoughts. I sincerely thank you both. </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">Judges note<br>Your forearms shall be pressed against your body throughout the roll and your fingers shall remain in your armpits. </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">Earlier attempts for reference:</div>
<div dir="auto"><iframe width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F5fdRcgUtMY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TfeMOI9bHvQ" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div>
</div>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>32 Elbow Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/32-elbow-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/32-elbow-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:51:39+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The elbow roll is quite a bit more difficult than the previous lay back rolls. Not as hard as the forward finishing clenched fist and brick rolls but still. Have a look at the preparations working up to the Brick roll Layback - they are&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WV8S09qxpSw" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The elbow roll is quite a bit more difficult than the previous lay back rolls. Not as hard as the forward finishing clenched fist and brick rolls but still. </p>
<p>Have a look at the preparations working up to the Brick roll Layback - they are the same as to the elbow roll and then some. </p>
<p>When I started trying the elbow roll I was amazed at how much lift I do get using my hand or fist. Not only is that lift gone in the elbow roll but there is a another more subtle difficulty. As I put my hand on the back of my head it is much harder for me to arch back. This is mostly a mental thing but also a bit of flexibility of the shoulder. When I try arching my head back in this position my elbow like to come forward. This means to me that I need to actively push my elbow out and down during the little sweep I can get. Don't get me wrong, I don't mean to push the elbow down for support like I can get from a paddle, just push it out so it lays parallel to the surface and don't point to the sky. If you push it down for support it will sink and our shoulders will knife. </p>
<p>My arching is more pronounced and I use both my legs to turn the qajaq. I've mentioned it several times before and I have a different feeling when using both legs in lay back versus forward finishing rolls. In lay back rolls I try to push my non-water leg out, like out to the gunwhale, in forward finishing rolls I push it down, like to the bottom of the qajaq. I've found it easier to push the non-water leg out in lay back rolls as I can arch my back more, or at least it feels easier. In forward finishing i crunch my abs in this position and pushing the non-water leg down is ok. I find more momentum with my legs pushing down if the timing is right. </p>
<p>As in all rolls, don't raise your head out of the water until last. I have good momentum in the roll in the video so I get away with it. </p>
<p>Strangely enough I set up very differently in the elbow roll than in all the other lay back rolls. I twist my torso so I face sideways, point the elbow forward and capsize. It feels like doing a face-plant into the water. Most people try to lean forward close to the fore deck and I guess that's fine but it doesn't work for me. </p>
<p>Lastly, hold your position - facing sideways or forward until your nose get very close to the surface before you un-tuck and sweep your torso. </p>
<p>Judges note: The hand shall stay on the back of your head throughout the whole roll. It is ok to use the other arm as counterweight. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>31 Brick Roll Layback</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/31-brick-roll-layback.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/31-brick-roll-layback.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:42:54+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The Brick roll Layback is mostly a mental difficulty. If you can pull off a layback hand roll this should not be too hard. Is it worth 9 points, well.... What I needed to work on progressing from the layback hand roll to the rock/brick&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PnRQTBA5j5o" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The Brick roll Layback is mostly a mental difficulty. If you can pull off a layback hand roll this should not be too hard. Is it worth 9 points, well....</p>
<p>What I needed to work on progressing from the layback hand roll to the rock/brick roll are a few things.<br>1. Start with the side sculling. Yes, the first manoeuvre on the list! Now I need to get both shoulders in the water, really arch my back to push my head down backwards into the water. I also do static brace using my free hand to push me further out from the qajaq. With a low volume qajaq as mine I don't need a paddle to do this but it feels good to have it at hand. In the floating position on my back I try to swing my upper body from as close to 90 degrees to the qajaq to my head touching the aft gunwale back and fourth simulating the body sweep in the layback roll. <br>2. When holding a 4 kg (ladies 3 kg) rock in my hand I don't want to put strain on my shoulder. To avoid that I hold the rock rather close to the gunwale and when I sweep my body simply let the rock drop. This will also put my arm in a awkward position pointing straight down in the water as l lay on the back deck. If I push the rock down I find that I stretch my shoulder badly and the momentum of the rock can pull me over. </p>
<p>That's if folks...</p>
<p>Judges note: It is ok to push the rock under the kayak as you complete the roll, and lift it out of the water as you sit up.   </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>30 Brick Roll Reverse Sweep</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/30-brick-roll-reverse-sweep.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/30-brick-roll-reverse-sweep.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:37:37+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The Brick roll Reverse Sweep has very much in common with the front to front brick roll so please read what I had to say about that first. I will mainly comment on differences here. I find the Brick roll Reverse Sweep a bit harder&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mwm8QVW0_6A" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The Brick roll Reverse Sweep has very much in common with the front to front brick roll so please read what I had to say about that first. I will mainly comment on differences here. </p>
<p>I find the Brick roll Reverse Sweep a bit harder than the Brick roll Front to Front since I haven't found how to use the sweep in an effective way. I simply move my body to the pry position as in the front to front roll and hope for the best. I need to practice getting more power out of the sweep, or maybe it's just how I feel when doing it? </p>
<p>My main challenge is to keep the brick/rock high in the water so it is at the surface as I reach the pry position, or "face down float". Not that there is much "float" holding a 4 kg rock over my head. If I succeed with the rock position I usually succeed, but as previously stated, there are no margins for errors. I try to use my legs to hold a "pressure" in my qajaq as i sweep and then as I push the rock down, crunch my abs and try to get my nose to my knee I want to really flip the qajaq to upright. Here's where an old guys anatomy can get in the way once in a while, to both lay "flat" with my shoulders on the surface and get my hips turned to be able to crunch. I get stuck from time to time, there is no way I can pull this roll off without a good warming up. </p>
<p>As always I'm not quite happy with my form in the video above but I got up, didn't I? <br>A little sculling at the end, well the roll would be accepted but depending on the judge a point may be taken off. </p>
<p>Judges note: Start holding the brick at the rear gunwale.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>29 Brick Roll Front to Front</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/29-brick-roll-front-to-front.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/29-brick-roll-front-to-front.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:31:10+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Now is this roll Brick F2F harder than the Clenched Fist F2F? Is it worth more points, well I am not sure. Both rolls are similar in their execution however the mental strain of holding a heavy brick or rock in my hand is very&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/p0EnMWD0FNM" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Now is this roll Brick F2F harder than the Clenched Fist F2F? Is it worth more points, well I am not sure. Both rolls are similar in their execution however the mental strain of holding a heavy brick or rock in my hand is very different. The biggest problem is handling the rock above water, to get a good grip on it, to find the flattest surface. Once capsized the weight is neglectable (almost) and the greater surface area compared to my clenched fist is a great help during the sweep and pry. But of course it is heavy and it pulls you down. </p>
<p>My path to getting the Brick Front to Front roll has ups and downs. This is a hard roll! If i miss out on one detail it will fail. I use a massive leg drive - both legs in opposite directions. I feel it is crucial to get the rock high enough towards the surface before the sweep and pry. To crunch hard to get low on the front deck is no easy task so work on the stretch for hamstrings and lower back.</p>
<p>My most common mistake is not to reach up to the surface enough.  I started working on the roll trying to hold the rock perpendicular to the qajaq but after some help I have found that a forward angle is easier. Second mistake is usually timing... There is very little room for timing errors. I can get every part right but I start the leg drive too early which results in not using the momentum from capsizing to the full extent - fail. Overthinking on the reaching for the surface will make my leg drive late and I crunch/bow into the water deeper instead of righting the last of the qajaq and swinging my torso over the front deck. </p>
<p>Positive training is also important for me. Last summer (-22) I failed and failed until I swallowed my ego and started with a small rock, fist-size, simply to succeed. I almost practiced failing too much, it was actually hard even with such a small rock since my mind was set on failing as soon as I had a rock in my hand. </p>
<p>Practice doesn't make Perfect - Practice makes Permanent! </p>
<p>Judges note: You may hold the rock whichever way you want but it must be in the active hand. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>28 Clenched Fist Layback</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/28-clenched-fist-layback.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/28-clenched-fist-layback.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:25:03+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Now this isn't a very hard roll, if you can do the Layback Hand roll this won't present any problems. A tiny bit more of everything and mainly leg drive. As you can see my palm isn't facing the sky all that clearly so this&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/K8L0TkWrFLs" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Now this isn't a very hard roll, if you can do the Layback Hand roll this won't present any problems. A tiny bit more of everything and mainly leg drive. As you can see my palm isn't facing the sky all that clearly so this was a bit sloppy. </p>
<p>Judges note: <br>The hand must be palm up during sweep and recovery. The fingers must be closed during the entire roll.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>27 Clenched Fist Reverse Sweep</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/27-clenched-fist-reverse-sweep.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/27-clenched-fist-reverse-sweep.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:16:04+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Yeah! Now we're talking! This roll takes all I got, not that its all that much. If you are struggling with this roll don't be discouraged, it takes time. Look on the bright side, you must be a great roller already and if David can&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sjnMRkZJ744" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Yeah! Now we're talking! This roll takes all I got, not that its all that much. If you are struggling with this roll don't be discouraged, it takes time. Look on the bright side, you must be a great roller already and if David can do it, it can't be all that hard. Right?!</p>
<p>For me this roll is mainly about getting out of that lovely relaxed meditative mode I'm in when I roll. I have to start using force, timing and be aggressive! Reaching out to get some support from that little surface I have in the sweep and forcefully flip the qajaq as early as possible. It's hard to have margins in this roll but to get any margins everything has to be timed and forcefully "relaxed". </p>
<p>Life isn't fair and neither is rolling. The individuals who can do the roll makes it look easy because you can see how they are relaxed. When I try something new I usually get tense - a sure sign that a roll is going to fail. So I get all mixed up doing this roll, I have to use force and I have to be smooth and relaxed. This is very much the same as in judo practice. I've been doing Judo for 15 years and to start with I was very tense, stiff and of course got thrown a lot. To be able to perform I have to be relaxed but not passive. </p>
<p>As you might have figured out I went through the Greenland Competition List in the pool session which I filmed so 5 seconds before the clip above I did the Clenched Fist F2F which I had to scull a bit to get up. That annoys me, shouldn't have to scull. So I'm a bit pissed off at myself when I did this one, and you can tell. It's a bit more aggressive, more power and I recovered fine. Could have been even more forcefully executed but I'm ok with this one. </p>
<p>Judges note: <br>The fingers must be closed during the entire roll. </p>
<p>A comment about judging, I feel that Greenland Rolling isn't about winning. I always do my best and play fair, like in golf where you are your own judge most of the time.<br>Yes, you can hold the ping-pong ball with your thumb and use your fingers for sweeping support, but do you want to earn points that way? Of course not! Personally I think that the ping-pong ball is used for the uninitiated audience. I don't need it to keep my fist clenched and the judge can't see what I'm doing under water so the judge doesn't need me to hold it. On the other hand do I get a "breather" when I paddle over to get the ball and to return it so it serves some function. <br>If I wanted to win I wouldn't share my path and tricks to succeed with the rolls either but if anyone get any help reading my story ...😃👍 </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>26 Clenched Fist Front to Front</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/26-clenched-fist-front-to-front.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/26-clenched-fist-front-to-front.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:10:29+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I can't make up my mind if i find the Clenched fist rolls more difficult than the Rock rolls. The forward finishing ones are really hard! So, how did I make them work? Legs! Up till now I have managed the rolls using only/mainly the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/T0aZmDv-2SU" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>I can't make up my mind if i find the Clenched fist rolls more difficult than the Rock rolls. The forward finishing ones are really hard! So, how did I make them work?</p>
<p>Legs! Up till now I have managed the rolls using only/mainly the water leg for drive. That wasn't enough for me any longer. I have to engage the "upper" leg as well. In the hand roll section I explained how I use my stationary hand to push. Now I also use the leg under that hand to push. I feel that I "flip" the qajaq around using both legs, one pull the other push combined with a turn of the hip. To have that hand on top of the gunwale is a great support to remember to push with my leg as well. You can see that my form is much better now than in the Norsaq rolls because I have to get into the correct positions. </p>
<p>Timing! Not much more to discuss on timing more than that I need to practice in a positive way, I need to succeed with my rolls. Go back to an easier one if I fail and practice form and timing. </p>
<p>Hand position! Same here, not much more to add other than that it is of great importance to reach all the way up to the surface. </p>
<p>Now, it's ok to do some sculling as I do in the video, but what did I do "wrong" or less perfect? <br>A number of things actually; 1. Hand not all the way to the surface. 2. Not enough force in my leg drive. 3. No actual sweep and the pry was lame to say the least. </p>
<p>Judges note: <br>The fingers must be closed during the entire roll.  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>25 Hand Roll Layback</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/25-hand-roll-layback.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/25-hand-roll-layback.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-24T12:03:15+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The Hand roll layback is quite easy. After I had succeeded with the Norsaq layback it wasn't hard to do the Hand version of it. So, do I stop my comments here... No of course not. This roll is my goto roll in my surf/rock&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kuSGC8okD1Y" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The Hand roll layback is quite easy. After I had succeeded with the Norsaq layback it wasn't hard to do the Hand version of it. So, do I stop my comments here... No of course not. This roll is my goto roll in my surf/rock hopping qajaq as I find it easier than to set up my paddle under water in current and waves. I always have a spare paddle when I'm not on rolling practice in case I loose or drop my primary. Not that I recommend dropping a paddle. I hold on to the tip of the paddle with my sweeping hand and do a Hand roll layback. </p>
<p>As I practice layback rolls I try to rely less and less on hands and arms. To come out of the water using only my torso is the ultimate goal and the Hand roll layback is a great progression. I seldom throw my non-sweeping arm over the back as a counterweight and I try to use my sweeping arm as a stabiliser. This creates a feeling of a firm core with fluttering arms.  As you can see in the video I almost immediately turn over on my back, trying to get my shoulders flat on the surface. This is a very active movement, not a passive float. Legs? Well yes, but they do not have to be as active as in the harder rolls, elbow/SJ but it's an opportunity to start practice using the non-water leg. More on that topic down the line.</p>
<p>Judges note: <br>The hand must be palm up during sweep and recovery. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
