<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Qajaq Rolling</title>
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com" />
    <updated>2023-01-27T11:26:49+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>David Täng</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://qajaqrolling.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>19 Roll with avataq</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/19-roll-with-avataq.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/19-roll-with-avataq.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-27T11:26:49+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I guess I'll have to post another video where the roll succeed. This is a great illustration of one of the difficulties with the avataq roll. I simply love the catapult when my friend get shot back into the water, thank you for letting me&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vEZqttFPvYI" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>I guess I'll have to post another video where the roll succeed. This is a great illustration of one of the difficulties with the avataq roll. I simply love the catapult when my friend get shot back into the water, thank you for letting me use the footage Johanna. <br>As you can see in the sequence above the hard part is twofold, the first to get the avataq (hunting float) around the bottom of the qajaq and then to make sure you don't fall over as it does. </p>
<p>It's not a really hard roll if you have the correct body mechanics in place but if you try it using your paddle only to complete the roll you will find yourself in trouble. A lot of lower body movement to get the qajaq to complete slightly more than 360 degrees rotation. Once I feel the avataq coming under the hull I relax my hips/lower body to stop the qajaq to start another roll. To keep the paddle in the water so I can brace is another good idea. </p>
<p>To be continued...</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>33 Straight Jacket Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:27:27+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Correct, I haven't made it yet. This is what I can tell you about my journey so far. Prerequisites: A strong will to succeed, the process can be a bit painful at times. A qajaq that fits you, low back deck, full contact with your&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F5fdRcgUtMY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Correct, I haven't made it yet. This is what I can tell you about my journey so far.</p>
<p>Prerequisites: <br>A strong will to succeed, the process can be a bit painful at times. <br>A qajaq that fits you, low back deck, full contact with your thighs. <br>Excellent twist in your torso (I'm not there yet)<br>An understanding of what supports you; water, shoulders, secondary stability, weight distribution inside and out. <br>You should be able to do an Elbow roll with some ease, double elbow as well. If not start there. </p>
<p>Yoga and stretching. YES! For me this is somewhat painful but makes all the difference. And it takes time so don't set a timetable, do what you can and things will come to you. </p>
<p>Qajaq: This is one of the reasons I got into SOF qajaq building, so I can build myself a qajaq which allows me to do a SJ roll. Not that the qajaq does anything for you but some attributes need to be fulfilled. My current one (TTD6 - TvångsTröja David #6 or Straight Jacket David #6) is great, built for this purpose alone. There are two issues with it, the masik is a tad too high and it's black, l loved my brown ones. The RRD5 (Rockhopping and Roll David#5) had a masik slightly lower and I had to push my knees under it, so I raised it 1 cm for TTD6 and now I regret it a bit. When I lean forward my arms touch the masik stopping me from getting low on the foredeck. This isn't a problem in forward finishing rolls since my arms are not in the way but....</p>
<p>The three main things I work on at the moment are:<br>Getting my shoulders flat and parallel to the surface as I reach up towards the sky before I start the backward sweep.<br>Getting my shoulders "wide" at the surface and still keep my elbows to my torso. As I push my shoulders out my hands like to slip out of my armpits and my elbows like to leave my body. It feels like a mental thing, well I'll let you know...<br>Timing! If I try to recover on the back deck too soon, the qajaq isn't passed the second stability far enough and I simply capsize it back over me. If I recover too late I don't have the righting momentum of the qajaq to pull me up the last bit to get past the tipping point. </p>
<p>With weight distribution I am thinking about the non-water leg. Should I push it out to the side to get a better weight distribution, counterweight or push it down to get more speed, more momentum in the qajaq? Perhaps it doesn't matter as long as I use it actively?</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>01 Side Sculling</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/01-side-sculling.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/01-side-sculling.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:27:03+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Easy? Well it can be, and not... Whenever I fail any back-finishing rolls I go back to basics to side and chest sculling. It's easy to start cheating, not using your complete range of motion and the tools available. To get a 2 point score&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-uXbEpTvyC8" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Easy? Well it can be, and not... Whenever I fail any back-finishing rolls I go back to basics to side and chest sculling. It's easy to start cheating, not using your complete range of motion and the tools available. <br>To get a 2 point score you need to show the judge that you have control of yourself and your qajaq. At least one shoulder in the water and tip the qajaq up to at least 90 degrees. Correct, you don't try to tip the qajaq over but to keep it flat in normal conditions but this is competition. Give the judge all you can so the scoring is easy, full 2 points per side. </p>
<p>As you practice, try to get both shoulders, your entire torso in the water, get your eyebrows wet, keep one hand "still" over your shoulder, sweep wide and slow. My example may not be the greatest but I'm practising. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Greenland Competition Rolling</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/greenland-competiton-rolling.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/greenland-competiton-rolling.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:27:40+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I would like to share with you how I got down to the Straight Jacket roll on the Greenland Rolling Competition list. Not instructions in particular. No, what I have been looking for on the net has been "What made it work for me?" A&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I would like to share with you how I got down to the Straight Jacket roll on the Greenland Rolling Competition list. Not instructions in particular. No, what I have been looking for on the net has been "What made it work for me?" A personal instructor and mentor would be perfect but I haven't got one so if you don't either - here is how I taught myself and learned the rolls. </p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7S-RA436fyU" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Greenland Paddles</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/greenland-paddles.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/greenland-paddles.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:27:56+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I started out with europaddles as I didn't know anything else. As I started looking for "my" feeling of both kayak and paddle I rather soon discovered greenland paddles. Last year I tried to paddle a europaddle again as I was playing in the surf&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__image align-left"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/7/trepaddlar.jpg" alt="" width="223" height="297" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/7/responsive/trepaddlar-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/7/responsive/trepaddlar-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/7/responsive/trepaddlar-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/7/responsive/trepaddlar-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/7/responsive/trepaddlar-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/7/responsive/trepaddlar-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>I started out with europaddles as I didn't know anything else. As I started looking for "my" feeling of both kayak and paddle I rather soon discovered greenland paddles. Last year I tried to paddle a europaddle again as I was playing in the surf but no... Can't and won't try to find the technique or feeling again. I'm lost to the GP and happy about it. I make my own but I love to try other GPs as well. Recently got to try one from Anders Thygesen, Norwegian Wood, and it was super! Back to the workshop and try to find what made Anders paddle work its way through the water in such a lovely way. That will be experiment number 32, yes I brand them and keep count just for fun. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Skin on Frame Qajaqs</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/skin-on-frame-qajaqs.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/skin-on-frame-qajaqs.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:28:13+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Oh how I love the extremely low volume East Greenland qajaqs. Why do I write "qajaq" and not kayak? Well, first because I'm a nerd 😁. Second, as I have grasped the use of the words, a qajaq is a traditional skin on frame kayak&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Oh how I love the extremely low volume East Greenland qajaqs. Why do I write "qajaq" and not kayak? Well, first because I'm a nerd 😁. Second, as I have grasped the use of the words, a qajaq is a traditional skin on frame kayak even if it hasn't been skinned with sealskin. A kayak can are normally built in other materials such as plastics, carbon fibre etc. A "kayak" with some may call "recreational" isn't really a qajaq - it looks a bit like a kayak but there is a Greenlandic word -"qarariaq" - what I think means "like a qajaq" or "almost a qajaq". To call a kayak a "boat" is not correct in my opinion. Not that it's wrong but a qajaq is a traditional hunting tool, and together with the dogsled are the two most important tools for surviving. So to honour the arctic culture and all the people who died while hunting in a qajaq I hope I do the right thing. Thirdly - it looks beautiful "Qajaq"! </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>D2 The D1 &quot;copy&quot; with modifications.</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/d2-the-d1-copy-with-modificatins.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/d2-the-d1-copy-with-modificatins.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:47:52+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    A friend asked to buy the D1 so I started building a "copy" in the winter/spring of 2017. Of course there are some modifications as you can see on the images. The cockpit is smaller and the masik sits a bit higher. Yes, the D2&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"></figure>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_0046.jpg" data-size="3840x2160"><img loading="lazy" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_0046-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="405"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_0047.jpg" data-size="3840x2160"><img loading="lazy" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_0047-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="405"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_0050.jpg" data-size="3840x2160"><img loading="lazy" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_0050-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="405"></a></figure>
</div></div>
<p>A friend asked to buy the D1 so I started building a "copy" in the winter/spring of 2017. Of course there are some modifications as you can see on the images. The cockpit is smaller and the masik sits a bit higher. Yes, the D2 isn't quite finished in the images above, the deckriggings are missing. I loved this qajaq and paddled it for four years. <br>It wasn't so much that I wanted to do modifications as the itch to start building again that decided me to sell D2. Selling wasn't an easy task, the qajaq is "mine" for a number of reasons, nothing adjustable, no seat, no backrest, no hatches, no room for gear. My legs and knees determine the fixed positions of the footrest and masik and thighsupport so the person buying it need to be able to fit. I put out ads summer and autumn but a very mild response. Eventually I built a D3 and I ended up giving the D2 away to a friend. After all, it has been frequently used year around for four years and is a very special qajaq. But the advertising had reached a small group of interested people, more to come... </p>
<p>A short video where I fail a F2F norsaq toll in my D2 qajaq. </p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/K_lTE9fCW7Y" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<figure class="post__video">
<figure class="post__video">
<figure class="post__video"></figure>
</figure>
</figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>D1 The first SoF Qajaq build</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/d1-the-first-sof-qajaq-build.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/d1-the-first-sof-qajaq-build.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:25:56+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    D1 was built in 2016 in the autumn/fall. My first attempt and it was really all that I'd hoped for. Soo proud. Built in my garage out of Spruce and Ash, ash for bending stock. I used the book "Building the Greenland kayak" by Christoffer&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0036.jpg" data-size="3840x2160"><img loading="lazy" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0036-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="405"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0039.jpg" data-size="3840x2160"><img loading="lazy" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0039-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="405"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0404.jpg" data-size="3840x2160"><img loading="lazy" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0404-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="405"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0462.jpg" data-size="3840x2160"><img loading="lazy" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/4/gallery/DSC_0462-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="405"></a></figure>
</div></div>
<p>D1 was built in 2016 in the autumn/fall. My first attempt and it was really all that I'd hoped for. Soo proud. <br>Built in my garage out of Spruce and Ash, ash for bending stock. I used the book "Building the Greenland kayak" by Christoffer Cunningham and I guess I spent 80 h building it and 80 h reading to understand everything in English, not the vocabulary you learn in school. The cloth was from Extreme Textile, nylon and the varnish Zar one part PU. I dyed it with stone pigment so the colour will stay as i took care to get UV protcective varnish as well. </p>
<p>I brought it to a pool session in january 2017 and a guy there looked me up and asked if he could buy it. I had by this time already got some ideas for minor changes so I agreed on the condition that I finish my second one before delivery so I could copy most of the D1. Sorry to say the guy backed out on me so I had two custom build qajaqs build for my skinny tall body. But if he hadn't asked to buy it I may not have started to build as many as I have so thanks anyway.  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>This site is my x-mas gift from my oldest son. I plan to fill it with Greenland Rolling images, videos, tips, failures and successes. Skin on frame builds, Greenland paddle builds and design. </title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/this-site-is-my-x-mas-gift-from-my-oldest-son-i-plan-to-fill-it-with-greenland-rolling-images-videos-tips-failures-and-successes-skin-on-frame-builds-greenland-paddle-builds-and-design.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/this-site-is-my-x-mas-gift-from-my-oldest-son-i-plan-to-fill-it-with-greenland-rolling-images-videos-tips-failures-and-successes-skin-on-frame-builds-greenland-paddle-builds-and-design.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-25T10:25:16+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    As you may know there is a website called Qajaq rolls hosted by Cristopher Crowhurst which is a great site not to be confused with mine. I hope to be a bit more personal and I like to share my path towards completing the rolls&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>As you may know there is a website called Qajaq rolls hosted by Cristopher Crowhurst which is a great site not to be confused with mine. I hope to be a bit more personal and I like to share my path towards completing the rolls on the Greenland Rolling competition list as well as discussions on Skin on frame building - what works for me and my mistakes. </p>
<p>As my Swedish friends may be a bit annoyed by the English I start out this way and may turn bi-lingual as time passes. Any audio will most likely be in Swedish...</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
