<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Qajaq Rolling</title>
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com" />
    <updated>2025-09-04T10:18:36+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>David T칛ng</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://qajaqrolling.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Gr칬nlandspaddlar, Norsaq och Harpuner</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/groenlandspaddlar-norsaq-och-harpuner.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/groenlandspaddlar-norsaq-och-harpuner.html</id>

        <updated>2025-02-12T12:27:13+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Gr칬nlandspaddlar Mina Paddlar 칛r l칛tta, eleganta och med skuldror som standard. P친 samma s칛tt som Qajaqer kan jag skr칛ddarsy din paddel! Normalt g칬r jag hela paddlar men om n친gon vill s친 kan jag s칛tta in en delning av kolfiber (Gearlabs Ferrule). Jag tillverkar paddlar av&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h1>Gr칬nlandspaddlar</h1>
<p>Mina Paddlar 칛r l칛tta, eleganta och med skuldror som standard. P친 samma s칛tt som Qajaqer kan jag skr칛ddarsy din paddel! Normalt g칬r jag hela paddlar men om n친gon vill s친 kan jag s칛tta in en delning av kolfiber (Gearlabs Ferrule).먝</p>
<p>Jag tillverkar paddlar av svensk gran, jag k칬per st칬rre bitar material och s친gar ut det som 칛r kvistfritt i m칬jligaste m친n. En standardpaddel 칛r gjord i sex delar som jag limmar ihop. Detta g칬r att eventuella svagheter i en bit kompenseras av de andra runt omkring samt att den inte sl친r sig, vrider sig. Normall칛ngd 칛r mellan 210-220 cm och avst친nget mellan skuldrorna 42 cm. 츿r inte det lite smalt mellan h칛nderna tycker n친gon? Kanske, det har passat mina kompisar i flera 친r efter de f친tt paddla med dem men vill du ha n친got annat m친tt s친 h칬r av dig, ingen extra kostnad. Bredden 칛r 70-80 mm vilket passar i de flesta milj칬er. Samma h칛r, vill du ha en smalare eller bredare s친 ordnar jag det. Vikten beror fr칛mst p친 kvalit칠n p친 virket men brukar hamna p친 mellan 650 - 850 gram.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250202_110831-2.jpg" alt="" width="234" height="520" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250202_110844.jpg" alt="" width="233" height="518" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/trepaddlar-2.jpg" alt="" width="216" height="288" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>Du kan ocks친 best칛lla en paddel med extra finesser som f칬rst칛rkta spetsar, annan f칛rg eller vad du vill. Jag kanske inte kan g칬ra allt men h칬r av dig s친 pratar vi om det. 游땕<a href="mailto:David.o.tang@gmail.com">David.o.tang@gmail.com</a></p>
<h1>Norsaq och harpuner</h1>
<p>En norsaq beh칬ver alla som har lite ambitioner kring sin rollning. I grund och botten 칛r det en bit tr칛 som du kan rolla med och kasta en harpun med. Ska du bara rolla s친 칛r det b칛ttre om den inte 칛r anpassad till en harpun.</p>
<p>Vill du kasta harpun s친 g칬r jag harpun och norsaq som passar. Du f친r en harpun med ett s친 kallat f칬rskaft som 칛r fastbundet med l칛derremmar. Dock ing친r inte spets, lina, eller avataq.<br>Det 칛r riktigt kul att l칛gga ut ett m친l i vattnet och f칬rs칬ka tr칛ffa. Kanske en grej till klubben och en liten t칛vling? D친 blir jag lycklig i och med att ni bidrar till att f칬ra traditionerna vidare.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/harpunkast_1.jpg" alt="" width="960" height="540" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250212_122137.jpg" alt="" width="299" height="665" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250212_122205.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="667" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Reverse Sweep Elbow Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/reverse-sweep-elbow-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/reverse-sweep-elbow-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2025-02-08T19:53:55+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Yes! The holy grail of Rolls... This roll is introduced in the Swedish Greenland Rolling Competition in 2025. Why? Isn't it impossible? Well, I may never be able to carry this one out but for all the great rollers out there this may be the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Yes! The holy grail of Rolls...</p>
<p>This roll is introduced in the Swedish Greenland Rolling Competition in 2025.</p>
<p>Why? Isn't it impossible?</p>
<p>Well, I may never be able to carry this one out but for all the great rollers out there this may be the utimate challange. I hope that someone in the next few years will carry this roll out, perhaps sooner... I really hope that it will be someone young! Come and beat us oldies!</p>
<p>I have tried the Reverse Sweep Elbow roll a couple of sessions and I'm not even close. This is a tough one but as I said - a challange. I really enjoy having a new goal, a new quest!</p>
<p>To be continued...</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Handcuff Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/handcuff-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/handcuff-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2025-02-21T14:07:39+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    What!? A new roll... on the competition list? Yes, this is a spoiler... well not for long. The Handcuff roll together with the Reverse Sweep Elbow roll is introduced to the Swedish Greenland Rolling competition in 2025. A rope loop is now part of your&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>What!? A new roll... on the competition list?</p>
<p>Yes, this is a spoiler... well not for long. The Handcuff roll together with the Reverse Sweep Elbow roll is introduced to the Swedish Greenland Rolling competition in 2025.</p>
<p>A rope loop is now part of your personal equipment (TBC, To be confirmed) and the diameter should be around 20cm (TBC). The roll is like a version of the Straight Jacket roll so basically everything from that post applies. <br>The new difficulty is that as I now have my hands behind my back, basically knuckle to knuckle, it is harder to "slide" up on the back deck than in the Straight Jacket. I have my arms in a better position so I can get "wide on the water" or at least wider... I need to arch my back a lot more than in the SJ so the "Camel" and "Cobra" pose will be used a lot during yoga practice. I started out holding my hands at my side, knuckles in. Then I moved the hands closer together behind my back until my fingertips touched. After that I thought I was home free - not so! It is harder than I thought to form fists or at least hold the rope loop as the final step. Now I haven't practiced more than one session but I would hold this roll almost, or as hard as the Straight Jacket roll. That may be revised but now I really feel my years and stiffness.</p>
<p>Update! Now I've had another session and found some tricks that work for me. The capsize can be slow if I do a "faceplant" with shoulders flat on the water. I find it hard to crunch with my hands on my back so I knife my shoulders until I reach the surface. I discovered that since my cockpit coaming is very far back my hands catch on it. In my qajaq I need to raise my hands rather high on my back to avoid getting stuck. When I got this worked out the Handcuff roll isn't that mysterious any more. Still not an easy one!</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="390" style="width: 700px; height: 390px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/T8Xvcb9jUHc" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Vad h칛nder n칛r jag best칛ller en kajak?</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/vad-haender-naer-jag-bestaeller-en-kajak.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/vad-haender-naer-jag-bestaeller-en-kajak.html</id>

        <updated>2025-04-28T20:01:14+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Lite mystiskt 칛r det... hur kan Kajakskr칛ddaren veta hur jag vill ha min kajak? L친t mig ber칛tta vad som h칛nder: 1. Vi pratas vid, telefon, chatt, Teams eller liknande, helst tr칛ffas vi. Jag vill veta vem du 칛r, hur brukar du paddla/rolla, vad anv칛nder du&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Lite mystiskt 칛r det... hur kan Kajakskr칛ddaren veta hur jag vill ha min kajak?</p>
<p>L친t mig ber칛tta vad som h칛nder:</p>
<p>1. Vi pratas vid, telefon, chatt, Teams eller liknande, helst tr칛ffas vi. Jag vill veta vem du 칛r, hur brukar du paddla/rolla, vad anv칛nder du idag (om n친got), vad vill du g칬ra/utveckla i din nya kajak? Din kunskapsniv친 avg칬r en del av designen.</p>
<p>2. Du f친r ange dina kroppsm친tt, som vikt, l칛ngd, avst친nd mellan sittben och h칛lar etc. Du f친r en lista och lite bilder p친 hur du ska m칛ta. Eventuellt l칛gger jag upp den nedan. H칛r kommer en ny aspekt in, hur flexibel 칛r du i kroppen? Vi kan ta den diskussionen privat men det ger vissa friheter om du 칛r flexibel men det viktiga 칛r att din kajak kommer att passa inte bara dina yttre kroppsm친tt utan hur du kan anv칛nda din kropp och kajak. Allt f칬r att det ska bli DIN kajak. Naturligtvis kommer andra att kunna paddla den men det 칛r DIG den 칛r perfekt till.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/Maetbild_David.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="324" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>3. Jag b칬rjar bygga, vill du s친 f친r du rapport fr친n mig efter varje byggdag s친 du ser vad som h칛nder och f친r se hur din kajak tar form. MEN, jag kan bara g칬ra s친 mycket utan dig.</p>
<p>4. Provning! Jo, det 칛r som hos skr칛ddaren, du f친r komma och prova innan allt 칛r klart. Om du vill virar vi in din kajak i plast s친 du kan prova den i vattnet ocks친, d친 ser vi exakt hur m친nga milimeter fribord du har och hur din kajak ligger i vattnet.<br>Vi ser till att fotst칬d hamnar exakt, att l친rst칬det hamnar p친 r칛tt st칛lle 칬ver l친ren, att masik blir lagom h칬g s친 att den inte hindrar om du b칬jer dig fram, med mera. "Allt" g친r att 칛ndra till dina 칬nskem친l i detta skede. Vill du s친 hj칛lper jag till med vad jag anser vara r칛tt f칬r dig men det 칛r du som best칛mmer.<br>Rollare brukar avsluta provsittningen i poolen med en f칬rsta roll. Det blir bara en eller ett par rollar d친 vi s칛llan har tuiliq p친 vid provsittning.</p>
<p>5. Jag bygger f칛rdigt din kajak enligt det vi kommit 칬verens om. F칬rst skelettet och sedan kl칛r jag den med ett nylontyg. Jag f칬redrar 240g per kvadratmeter i tygtjocklek men du kan f친 ett tjockare tyg p친 460g per kvadratmeter. Skillnaden 칛r mest k칛nsla och kanske ett par hekto i vikt, det tjockare tyget absorberar mer lack ocks친. N칛st sista steg 칛r lackning, h칛r kan du f친 v칛lja din egen f칛rg! Jag anv칛nder pigment fr친n Claessons Tr칛tj칛ra s친 allt de har kan du v칛lja mellan. Detta 칛r faktiskt ett av de tuffaste valen f칬r de kunder jag haft... Jag v칛ljer alltid en ljust brun till mig sj칛lv... fast jag kan kanske t칛nka om.</p>
<p>6. Kajaken 칛r din! Vi 칛r troligtvis goda v칛nner du och jag vid det h칛r laget. Som du m칛rker vill jag verkligen att det ska bli riktigt bra. Jag 칬nskar att du ska f친 uppleva den gl칛djen och k칛nslan som en Skr칛ddarsydd kajak kan ge. Den blir verkligen personlig. Dessutom blir jag lycklig var g친ng jag lyfter upp min p친 biltaket! Cirka 11-12 kg brukar vikten sluta p친. Sm친 kajaker kan hamna lite l칛gre men det beror p친 det tr칛 jag f친r tag p친 ocks친. En turkajak kan bli 1-2 kg tyngre men 14 kg kajak 칛r fortfarande en fr칬jd att lyfta upp p친 bilen.<br><br></p>
<p>Nedan 칛r en Turkajak, inspirerad av Anas Acuta. Byggd till min fru...</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/IMG_20230507_122342.jpg" alt="" width="4000" height="1800" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Kajakskr칛ddaren</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/kajakskraeddaren.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/kajakskraeddaren.html</id>

        <updated>2025-05-25T14:02:55+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Vad 칛r nu detta, Svenska!? Jo, jag bygger nu Skin on Frame kajaker till andra 칛n mig sj칛lv! 游땶 I och med att DU som kan t칛nkas vara intresserad troligen bor n칛ra mig (Norden), s친 k칛nner jag att det 칛r mer personligt att skriva p친&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Vad 칛r nu detta, Svenska!?</p>
<p>Jo, jag bygger nu Skin on Frame kajaker till andra 칛n mig sj칛lv! 游땶 <br>I och med att DU som kan t칛nkas vara intresserad troligen bor n칛ra mig (Norden), s친 k칛nner jag att det 칛r mer personligt att skriva p친 svenska. Hur g친r det till att best칛lla en kajak fr친n mig? <a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/vad-haender-naer-jag-bestaeller-en-kajak.html">Kolla h칛r!</a></p>
<p>Vill ni ha en tuiliq som passar till er qajaq s친 s칛ljer jag RUGD tuiliqs! Riktigt bra kvalite, 3 mm neoprene, sn칬rning runt ansiktet, elastiskt kardborreband kring handlederna. Endast svarta f칬r tillf칛llet.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/RUGD1.jpg" alt="" width="3840" height="2160" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>En Skin on Frame kajak 칛r en traditionellt byggd kajak som de tillverkats under 100-tals kanske 1000-tals 친r p친 Gr칬nland och i Arktis. Den best친r av ett skelett i tr칛 som sedan kl칛s med duk, traditionellt s칛lskinn, som sedan g칬rs vattent칛tt med lack, traditionellt anv칛ndes fett och sp칛ck. En kajak som 칛r byggd p친 detta s칛tt kan 칛ven betecknas Qajaq som 칛r den Gr칬nl칛ndska stavningen.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/DSC_0410.JPG" alt="" width="3840" height="2160" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-xs.JPG 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-sm.JPG 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-md.JPG 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-2xl.JPG 1600w"></figure>
<p>Helst bygger jag dedikerade rollkajaker, det 칛r jag b칛st p친, men om du vill ha en dagsturs- eller tur-kajak s친 g친r det ocks친. Kajaken byggt till DIG, enligt dina kroppsm친tt och till dina 칬nskem친l.</p>
<p><strong>Rollkajak</strong>: P친 SM i G칬teborg -24 var faktiskt ganska m친nga av mina kajaker med 칛ven om de absolut flesta faktiskt var byggda f칬r min kropp. Plats nummer 1, 2, 3 och 5 har kajaker som jag byggt. Det s칛ger lite om hur bra det blir med en dedikerad rollkajak. Denna kajak 칛r extremt liten volym i, vi str칛var efter 15 mm fribord som 칛r gr칛nsen f칬r t칛vling. Den 칛r rak i k칬llinjen, platt i botten akter칬ver och lite mer V form f칬r칬ver. Ett runt f칬rd칛ck ger en snabb och l칛tt roll, ett platt och l친gt och platt akterd칛ck utan ett irriterade ryggst칬d som biter sig in i korsryggen ger dig en m칬jlighet att lyckas med till och med en Straight Jacket roll. Med bredd och h칬jd f칬r l친rst칬den som anpassas p친 millimetern till din kropp och stil f친r du en kajak som inte kommer att s칛tta n친gra begr칛nsningar.</p>
<p><strong>Dagstur:</strong>Liknar rollkajaken till stora delar med nu 칬kar vi p친 volymen lite s친 vi inte f친r in vatten i v친gorna. Nu f친r du 칛ven m칬jlighet att ta med dig lite mats칛ck och annan packning. En lite bekv칛mare kajak men du v칛ljer om du vill l친ta den g친 친t roll- eller tur- h친llet.</p>
<p><strong>Turkajak: </strong>Vill du ha en kajak som 칛r mer 친t det "vanliga" h친llet som 칛r en Skin on Frame variant av till exempel en Anas Acuta (Valley) eller liknande s친 bygger jag g칛rna en s친dan. Turkajaker utrustas g칛rna med vattent칛ta p친sar (stora avl친nga) som fyller upp utrymmet framf칬r fotst칬den och akter om ryggen f칬r s칛kerhet och packm칬jligheter. Man kan ocks친 anv칛nda en s친 kallad "SeaSock" som 칛r som en mjuk sittbrunn. <br>Ska du p친 veckol친ng tur? Kontakta Kajakkspesialistens Anders Thygessen och be honom bygga en Baidarka.</p>
<p>Jag g칬r 칛ven gr칬nlandspaddlar - hela eller delbara, norsaq och harpuner (med norsaq).</p>
<p>츿r du intresserad s친 kontakta mig p친:</p>
<p><a href="mailto:david.o.tang@gmail.com">david.o.tang@gmail.com</a></p>
<p>s친 kan vi prata vidare.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/David-Saekerhet-1280-720.jpg" alt="" width="505" height="284" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h2>Fj칛rde leveransen fr친n Kajakskr칛ddaren!</h2>
<p>츿ven denna Qajaq kommer att f친 bo i Danmark, har den starka Danska kronan med saken att g칬ra??? En utpr칛glad rollqajaq som Frank ska ha f칬r att utmana Jakob (D13) i de Danska M칛sterskapen i Gr칬nlandsroll. Jag blev lite 칬verraskad n칛r f칛rgen best칛mdes snabbt och best칛mt till orange! Det blev ju s친 snyggt! Mycket positiv till denna nyansen! Linjerna blev ocks친 som jag hade visualiserat s친 jag hoppas att den rollar som Frank vill att den ska rolla.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250510_114331.jpg" alt="" width="4000" height="1800" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250510_114500.jpg" alt="" width="4000" height="1800" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h2>Tredje leveransen fr친n Kajakskr칛ddaren!</h2>
<p>D-15 numera d칬pt till M친sart (eller Mozart) blev en utmaning. En dedikerad rollkajak till en l칛tt person!!! Den 칛r den l칛gsta, minst fr친n k칬l till relingen, som jag n친gonsin byggt. 11 cm i totaldjup om jag minns r칛tt! M칛t upp 11 cm och se efter, det 칛r v칛ldigt lite volym. M칬nster och f칛rgvalet - oj! En hel del prat och diskussioner, sedan fick jag best칛mma sj칛lv. Jag gjorde mitt b칛sta, kanske skulle jag l친tit kunden komma och lacka den sj칛lv...</p>
<p>Den 칛r mycket omtyckt vad jag har f칬rst친tt och jag har f친tt en ny v칛n!<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/Masart4.jpeg" alt="" width="2048" height="1312" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-md.jpeg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-lg.jpeg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-xl.jpeg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-2xl.jpeg 1600w"></figure>
<h2><figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/Masart2.jpeg" alt="" width="254" height="565" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-md.jpeg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-lg.jpeg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-xl.jpeg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-2xl.jpeg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/Masart6-2.jpeg" alt="" width="442" height="199" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-md.jpeg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-lg.jpeg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-xl.jpeg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-2xl.jpeg 1600w"></figure></h2>
<h2>Andra leveransen fr친n Kajakskr칛ddaren!</h2>
<p>D-14 (Dagstur - Roll) togs emot den 29 december 2024. Som jag uppfattade det var kajaken mycket efterl칛ngtad och 칛lskad redan vid leverans. 游땘 Detta var ett special uppl칛gg d칛r det ingick extra allt! Pulley system f칬r att f친 in packning eller flytkroppar i f칬ren och aktern, skedda som 칛r avtagbar, en paddel nummer 45 samt instruktion f칬r att g칬ra en handroll. Handrollen satt 3-4 g친nger p친 var sida under lektionen, f친r se om den sitter... Det var ett k칛nslofyllt m칬te och avsked, D-14 칛r vacker och inte bara en rollkajak. D-14 har en design f칬r att b친de rolla utm칛rkt samt vara bekv칛m p친 dagsturer. Jag hoppas att ni kommer finna mycket gl칛dje tillsammans. F칛rgen 칛r en utblandad Milori-bl친.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal); outline: 3px solid rgba(var(--color-primary-rgb), 0.55) !important;" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250207_145711.jpg" alt="" width="192" height="426" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal); outline: 3px solid rgba(var(--color-primary-rgb), 0.55) !important;" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20241229_144927.jpg" alt="" width="191" height="425" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250207_145807.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="225" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h2>F칬rsta leveransen fr친n Kajakskr칛ddaren!</h2>
<p>D-13 (Rollkajak) togs emot av sin best칛llare fredagen den 13 December 2024. Jag 칛r s칛ker p친 att kajaken kommer att f친 ett bra hem hos den tv친faldige Danske M칛staren! Den provrollades p친 Kungsbackafjorden under dagen och de b친da verkar komma mycket bra 칬verens. Ryktet s칛ger att Straight Jacket rollen 칛r n칛ra nu...</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2.jpg" alt="" width="180" height="400" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Skin on Frame Material</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/skin-on-frame-material.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/skin-on-frame-material.html</id>

        <updated>2023-12-26T15:07:58+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I've been asked several times where to get material for a Skin on Frame SoF build in Sweden or northen Europe. Here is a list of my suppliers which I hope will be useful for You as well. Lumber: I go to my local lumberstore&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I've been asked several times where to get material for a Skin on Frame SoF build in Sweden or northen Europe. Here is a list of my suppliers which I hope will be useful for You as well.</p>
<p>Lumber: I go to my local lumberstore for all straight lumber. I spend time to select the best Spruce lumber I can find. My suggestion is to buy a bit larger dimensions than you need and cut around the worst knots, also to laminate the gunwales to avoid weak areas. Byggmax is my store in Kungsbacka.</p>
<p>Bending stock: I haven't found "green" or freshly cut bending stock yet but I keep looking. In the meantime I buy Ash planks from <a href="https://abitra.se/produkt/planhyvlat-ovriga-traslag/">Abi Tr칛 in Fr칬lunda (Gothenburg)</a>. Same procedure here to find straight grain planks and so far the material I've got is very good. Last build (number 10) I didn't break any ribs but usually up to a third of the ribs break.</p>
<p>Cloth: The best cloth I've found is excellent! Provided by Marcin Bober in Poland. Marcin hasn't set up a website yet but is very professional in everything he delivers. His english is understandable albeit not perfect but don't let that discourage you. Also don't be alarmed as you may be asked to use his wifes PayPal account, <a href="https://www.mimisoapery.com/en/">Mimi's Soapery.</a> Among other things Marcin provides Nylon cloth of two thicknesses, 260 grams per square meter and 430 grams per square meter. I've used both and I'm very happy with it. To get in contact with Marcin check Facebook or write me and I'll set you up.먝</p>
<p>Thread/Artificial Sinew: Same supplier as above Marcin Bober! Ask for your specific colour, you may be in luck.</p>
<p>PU varnish: Same supplier as above for 2-part PU, Marcin Bober! Works great! I sometimes use Coelan 1-part PU which I like even better as I don't have to mix it and it handles great. It cost about 3-4 times as much as Marcin's PU so it is very doubtful if it is worth it. I get Coelan from <a href="https://www.toplicht.de/en/paint-boatbuilding/paint-conservation/coelan-coating/3150/coelan-boat-coating-transparent-gloss-finish?number=2621-075">Toplicht in Hamburg.</a> Three cans of 750 ml is sufficient.</p>
<p>Leather cord: I love to use the traditional deck riggings using leather cords and sliders. I buy round english leather cord from <a href="https://www.tjaderlader.se/rundrem-natur-vegetabilgarvad-engelska">Tj칛derl칛der</a>. 5 mm for the rigging front and aft of the cockpit and 7 mm for loops front and aft to stick your paddle into. 5 m of 5 mm and 0,5-1 m of 7mm cord. They may not be the cheapest but the best I've found. Sorry to say but I don't think they have a webpage in english, send me a mail if you need help.</p>
<p>Pigments: I use pigment in the second layer of varnish to "dye" my qajaqs. As the pigment is basically crushed stone it doesn't fade and is in itself an UV protection. My local supplier is <a href="https://claessons.com/pigment/">Claessons Tr칛tj칛ra</a> at Ring칬n, Gothenburg. They also have the best linseed oil! The colours are of course limited but you can always mix them. In stock they have multiple variations of: White, Red, Yellow, Terra (brown), Umbra (brown), Green, Blue, and Black.</p>
<p>If I can do anything to help or assist you in your build, don't hesitate to contact me at <a href="mailto:david.o.tang@gmail.com">david.o.tang@gmail.com</a> or via Facebook, Messenger, Instagram etc.</p>
<p>Note: I don't get any benefits from the companies mentioned above. I have been searching for suppliers in my region of the world for 5-6 years and this is the current list.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Useful links</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/useful-links.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/useful-links.html</id>

        <updated>2023-12-26T15:12:28+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    As always, a lot of people have done a lot of work a lot better than I could ever do. To start with; how do you get your first roll. I don't intend to teach the first roll as others can do that better. Perhaps&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>As always, a lot of people have done a lot of work a lot better than I could ever do.</p>
<p>To start with; how do you get your first roll. I don't intend to teach the first roll as others can do that better. Perhaps I can help in person, but that's off the scope for the webpage. My recommendation is to find professional rolling teachers locally. If they are hard to find then get the DVD:</p>
<p><a href="https://kayakways.net/videos/digital-downloads/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"This is the Roll" by Cheri Perry and Turner Wilson of Kayakways</a>.</p>
<p>You can find it as a Disc as well on their site: <a href="http://www.kayakways.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.kayakways.net</a></p>
<p>Excellent instructions and animations on Eiichi Eto's page <a href="http://www.storm-on.com/">Storm On</a></p>
<p>Paddlegear at <a href="https://www.chillcheater.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reed Chillcheater</a></p>
<p>Greenland paddles at <a href="https://gramkajak.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gram Kayak</a></p>
<p>Skin on Frame, Norwegian Wood paddles and more with Anders Thygesen at <a href="https://www.yourvismawebsite.com/kajakkspesialisten-as-1/lang-EN" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kajakkspesialisten</a><br>Note that Anders sells Brooks Tuiliqs!</p>
<p>My club "<a href="www.rolltokarna.se">The Rolling Lunatics" or "Rolltokarna</a>" <figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/Rolltokarnalogga.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="295" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>34 Paddling Upside Down</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/34-paddling-upside-down.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/34-paddling-upside-down.html</id>

        <updated>2025-09-04T10:18:36+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This manoeuvre is pretty straight forward. I put my paddle under the qajaq, capsize and go. NEVER PRACTICE WITHOUT A FRIEND! And a friend who known what to do and can help you recover if you pass out! Now there are a few hint to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OTCWnZb-3dY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>This manoeuvre is pretty straight forward. I put my paddle under the qajaq, capsize and go.</p>
<p>NEVER PRACTICE WITHOUT A FRIEND! And a friend who known what to do and can help you recover if you pass out!</p>
<p>Now there are a few hint to be able to go far...</p>
<p>First of all - go straight! The points awarded are calculated from the straight line and I normally have to paddle next to a line in the water with distance markings. If the water is clear it can be possible to see the line and adjust my path to it. I get 1 point for the first 3 meters and 1 additional point for every two meters after that. 5 meters is 2 points, so is 6 meters.</p>
<p>I have seen paddlers rocking the qajaq to get the paddle deeper in the water as in a sprint stroke. That is a good idea both for power and for going straight.</p>
<p>To get a low profile under water is beneficial, lower drag, longer distance. I try to have my nose on the deck but it's hard. Hard to see where I'm going and hard because I compress my lungs.</p>
<p>The most important aspect of this manoeuvre is to hold my breath for a looooong time. I have got some help from free divers.</p>
<p>Get the area between your eyes and nose wet! This triggers the diving reflex!</p>
<p>1. How to breathe before going under. Inhale x seconds and exhale 2*x seconds, example: Inhale 4 seconds and exhale 8 seconds.</p>
<p>2. Hold your breath until you get contractions for at least one time, two is better if you have time left. After you've held your breath go back to 1. until your pulse is low again.</p>
<p>3. Take two very deep breaths before you capsize and start paddling. Fill your stomach, lungs and mouth with as much air as you can in your second breath.</p>
<p>As practice in/under water is potentially dangerous I practice mostly on land. What I'm really pracitcing is CO2 tolerance and land practice is just as good as in the water for this purpose. I practice in two ways, static and dynamic. Static practice in an armchair I set up in the same way as described above, breathe, hold my breath until contractions, breathe, hold again and relax my body. Relaxing is key since the body doesn't consume oxygene and produce CO2 as quickly. Dynamic practice mimics the effort you have to make while paddling. I walk! As I walk i count the steps. But that seems very unprecise, not really. A slow pace doesn't produce as much CO2 and I can walk for a longer period of time. A fast pace produce more CO2 but as the cadence is higher I take more steps. I only count steps as I walk. When I walk I try to be alone in the woods since this look very silly. The same procedure as described above, stand still and breathe, hold my breath and walk until I get contractions, stop and breathe, hold and walk again.</p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">When I practice I rarely measure my distance, more counting the seconds or strokes I make. Counting strokes are easier, seconds have a tendency for me to speed up as I get a bit stressed under water.</span></p>
<p>Practice paddling upside down! There are a lot of points go gain and it's not very difficult. It can be worth as much as a Straight Jacket Roll... (23 meters = 11 points)</p>
<p>Judges note: The distance is measured along the straight marked line.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>33 Straight Jacket Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2024-04-04T12:01:37+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I have finally made it. With the excellent help and instructions of Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and J칬rgen Fagereng Wessel! Thank you! This is an excellent example of how hands on instruction is invaluable to written instructions. I posted the instructions I got from Anne-Sofie and J칬rgen&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mPk2acArQCs?si=Y4M_DS8azyKkx27G" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>I have finally made it. With the excellent help and instructions of Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and J칬rgen Fagereng Wessel! Thank you! This is an excellent example of how hands on instruction is invaluable to written instructions. I posted the instructions I got from Anne-Sofie and J칬rgen earlier this spring but couldn't make out what I really needed to do. I invited them to come from Norway, they did and they taught me.</p>
<p>This is what I can tell you about my journey so far.</p>
<p>Prerequisites:<br>- A strong will to succeed, the process can be a bit painful at times.<br>- A qajaq that fits you, low back deck, full contact with your thighs.<br>- Good twist in your torso.<br>- An understanding of what supports you; water, shoulders, secondary stability, weight distribution inside and out.<br>- You should be able to do an Elbow roll with some ease, double elbow as well. If not start there.</p>
<p>Yoga and stretching. YES! For me this is somewhat painful but makes all the difference. And it takes time so don't set a timetable, do what you can and things will come to you.</p>
<p>Qajaq: This is one of the reasons I got into SOF qajaq building, so I can build myself a qajaq which allows me to do a SJ roll. Not that the qajaq does anything for you but some attributes need to be fulfilled. My current one (T2D5 - Tv친ngsTr칬ja David #5 or Strait Jacket David #5) is great, built for this purpose alone. There are two issues with it, the masik is a tad too high and it's black, l loved my brown ones. The R2D4 (Rockhopping and Roll David#4) had a masik slightly lower and I had to push my knees under it, so I raised it 1 cm for T2D5 and now I regret it a bit. When I lean forward my arms touch the masik stopping me from getting low on the foredeck. This isn't a problem in forward finishing rolls since my arms are not in the way but....<br>Padding and a snug fit is vital for this roll. Both at the masik and at the hips. If your hips slide down in the qajaq to the water gunwale it's very hard to get past the secondary stability and on to the back deck. I have now padded my hips as much as I can without restricting butt/hip movement.</p>
<p>The main things I work on at the moment are:<br>Getting my shoulders flat and parallel to the surface as I reach up towards the sky before I start the backward sweep.</p>
<p>As I get to the static brace position I push my head back and try to keep my shoulders flat. I can now stay in the static brace - straight jacket style - if my timing is a bit off and I can't recover in one motion. It's clear to me now that timing is important but not crucial.<br><br>To recover to the back deck I need to ease up with my lower back first, then chest and head out of the water last. This is what Anne-Sofie and J칬rgen wrote to me and later showed in detail.</p>
<h3>Additional sources:</h3>
<p>I also got this answer from Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and J칬rgen Fagereng Wessel on Facebook:</p>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>Straitjacket roll learning process:</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>I assume you already know the hand and elbow rolls.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>I split most back ending rolls in two parts:</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>1) the capsized to balance brace and</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>2) balance brace to back deck.</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>For the straitjacket roll getting the first part is a matter of timing, strong hip/knee drive and sufficient twisting of upper body. The second part is what most people seem to struggle with. If you manage to use the momentum from the first part that is great, but I found that it was easier to simply learn it from balance brace.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>Again, good twist of upper body is important, so is backward flexibility (practice the cobra stance in yoga).</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>I practiced a lot of balance bracing! Then it was beginning to go from balance brace to back deck with hands folded, and repeating while gradually moving the hands closer to the correct straitjacket position. In the beginning I found it helps moving my sea leg over to the other side in the kayak (every bit helps).</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>The kayak matters a lot, so does padding and fitting. I can not do the straitjacket roll in many kayaks, and I have some padding under front of the kayak (like a padded masik) and some at the hips to keep me from slipping too far to one side of the kayak. If it is too tight it limits my movement and twisting.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>It is important to try to use the lower back muscles to try to get the lower back up on the back deck, not just the upper torso and head.</em></div>
</div>
<h3>I found this on Helen Wilsons site <a href="http://www.greenlandorbust.org">www.greenlandorbust.org</a></h3>
<p><em>Often when first attempting the Straitjacket Roll, the paddler tries to 랍weep onto the back deck, and essentially bumps into it. They can hang out there all day (breathing), but not actually get onto the deck. Does this sound familiar? In this description, the 랍weep is the problem. This 랍weep usually works with a hand roll, fist roll, brick roll and sometimes even the Elbow Roll, but it will not work with the Straightjacket Roll. For the Straightjacket Roll, you need to think of your upper body as a lever, and instead of trying to 랍weep onto the back deck, push your upper body toward the ground, which will give you the leverage to fully recover. Following are the steps to a successful Straightjacket Roll (described with a right-side recovery):</em></p>
<p><em> Place your arms against your chest with your fingers and thumbs under your armpits.</em></p>
<p><em> Capsize to the left with your shoulders parallel to the side of the kayak and your forehead down (this will give you a rounded spine).</em></p>
<p><em> RELAX until your body gets to the highest position possible on the right side of the kayak (your shoulders should be parallel to the surface).</em></p>
<p><em> Throw your upper body toward the ground, using your back as a lever and keeping your shoulders parallel to the surface. Simultaneously, drive hard with the right knee.</em></p>
<p><em> Slide up onto the back deck (your head may hit the side of the kayak during the recovery).</em></p>
<p><em> Helen</em></p>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto">Two pros giving their thoughts. I sincerely thank you both.</div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto">Judges note<br>Your forearms shall be pressed against your body throughout the roll and your fingers shall remain in your armpits.</div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto">Earlier attempts for reference:</div>
<div dir="auto"><iframe width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F5fdRcgUtMY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TfeMOI9bHvQ" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div>
</div>
<p></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>32 Elbow Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David T칛ng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/32-elbow-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/32-elbow-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2024-04-04T11:54:06+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The elbow roll is quite a bit more difficult than the previous lay back rolls. Not as hard as the forward finishing clenched fist and brick rolls but still. Have a look at the preparations working up to the Brick roll Layback - they are&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WV8S09qxpSw" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The elbow roll is quite a bit more difficult than the previous lay back rolls. Not as hard as the forward finishing clenched fist and brick rolls but still.</p>
<p>Have a look at the preparations working up to the Brick roll Layback - they are the same as to the elbow roll and then some.</p>
<p>When I started trying the elbow roll I was amazed at how much lift I do get using my hand or fist. Not only is that lift gone in the elbow roll but there is a another more subtle difficulty. As I put my hand on the back of my head it is much harder for me to arch back. This is mostly a mental thing but also a bit of flexibility of the shoulder. When I try arching my head back in this position my elbow like to come forward. This means that I need to actively push my elbow out and down during the little sweep I get. Don't get me wrong, I don't mean to push the elbow down for support like I can get from a paddle, just push it out so it lays parallel to the surface and don't point to the sky. If you push it down for support it will sink and our shoulders will knife.</p>
<p>My arching is more pronounced and I use both my legs to turn the qajaq. I've mentioned it several times before and I have a different feeling when using both legs in lay back versus forward finishing rolls. In lay back rolls I try to push my non-water leg out, like out to the gunwhale, in forward finishing rolls I push it down, like to the bottom of the qajaq. I've found it easier to push the non-water leg out in lay back rolls as I can arch my back more, or at least it feels easier. In forward finishing i crunch my abs in this position and pushing the non-water leg down is ok. I find more momentum with my legs pushing down if the timing is right.</p>
<p>As in all rolls, don't raise your head out of the water until last. I have good momentum in the roll in the video so I get away with it.</p>
<p>Strangely enough I set up very differently in the elbow roll than in all the other lay back rolls. I twist my torso so I face sideways, point the elbow forward and capsize. It feels like doing a face-plant into the water. Most people try to lean forward close to the fore deck and I guess that's fine but it doesn't work for me.</p>
<p>Lastly, hold your position - facing sideways or forward until your nose get very close to the surface before you un-tuck and sweep your torso.</p>
<p>Judges note: The hand shall stay on the back of your head throughout the whole roll. It is ok to use the other arm as counterweight.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
