<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Qajaq Rolling</title>
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com" />
    <updated>2025-05-25T14:02:55+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>David Täng</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://qajaqrolling.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Grönlandspaddlar, Norsaq och Harpuner</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/groenlandspaddlar-norsaq-och-harpuner.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/groenlandspaddlar-norsaq-och-harpuner.html</id>

        <updated>2025-02-12T12:27:13+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Grönlandspaddlar Mina Paddlar är lätta, eleganta och med skuldror som standard. På samma sätt som Qajaqer kan jag skräddarsy din paddel! Normalt gör jag hela paddlar men om någon vill så kan jag sätta in en delning av kolfiber (Gearlabs Ferrule). Jag tillverkar paddlar av&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h1>Grönlandspaddlar</h1>
<p>Mina Paddlar är lätta, eleganta och med skuldror som standard. På samma sätt som Qajaqer kan jag skräddarsy din paddel! Normalt gör jag hela paddlar men om någon vill så kan jag sätta in en delning av kolfiber (Gearlabs Ferrule).  </p>
<p>Jag tillverkar paddlar av svensk gran, jag köper större bitar material och sågar ut det som är kvistfritt i möjligaste mån. En standardpaddel är gjord i sex delar som jag limmar ihop. Detta gör att eventuella svagheter i en bit kompenseras av de andra runt omkring samt att den inte slår sig, vrider sig. Normallängd är mellan 210-220 cm och avstånget mellan skuldrorna 42 cm. Är inte det lite smalt mellan händerna tycker någon? Kanske, det har passat mina kompisar i flera år efter de fått paddla med dem men vill du ha något annat mått så hör av dig, ingen extra kostnad. Bredden är 70-80 mm vilket passar i de flesta miljöer. Samma här, vill du ha en smalare eller bredare så ordnar jag det. Vikten beror främst på kvalitén på virket men brukar hamna på mellan 650 - 850 gram.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250202_110831-2.jpg" alt="" width="234" height="520" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110831-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250202_110844.jpg" alt="" width="233" height="518" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250202_110844-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/trepaddlar-2.jpg" alt="" width="216" height="288" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/trepaddlar-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>Du kan också beställa en paddel med extra finesser som förstärkta spetsar, annan färg eller vad du vill. Jag kanske inte kan göra allt men hör av dig så pratar vi om det. 😊<a href="mailto:David.o.tang@gmail.com">David.o.tang@gmail.com</a></p>
<h1>Norsaq och harpuner</h1>
<p>En norsaq behöver alla som har lite ambitioner kring sin rollning. I grund och botten är det en bit trä som du kan rolla med och kasta en harpun med. Ska du bara rolla så är det bättre om den inte är anpassad till en harpun. </p>
<p>Vill du kasta harpun så gör jag harpun och norsaq som passar. Du får en harpun med ett så kallat förskaft som är fastbundet med läderremmar. Dock ingår inte spets, lina, eller avataq. <br>Det är riktigt kul att lägga ut ett mål i vattnet och försöka träffa. Kanske en grej till klubben och en liten tävling? Då blir jag lycklig i och med att ni bidrar till att föra traditionerna vidare. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/harpunkast_1.jpg" alt="" width="960" height="540" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/harpunkast_1-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250212_122137.jpg" alt="" width="299" height="665" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122137-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/IMG_20250212_122205.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="667" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/42/responsive/IMG_20250212_122205-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Reverse Sweep Elbow Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/reverse-sweep-elbow-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/reverse-sweep-elbow-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2025-02-08T19:53:55+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Yes! The holy grail of Rolls... This roll is introduced in the Swedish Greenland Rolling Competition in 2025. Why? Isn't it impossible? Well, I may never be able to carry this one out but for all the great rollers out there this may be the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Yes! The holy grail of Rolls... </p>
<p>This roll is introduced in the Swedish Greenland Rolling Competition in 2025. </p>
<p>Why? Isn't it impossible? </p>
<p>Well, I may never be able to carry this one out but for all the great rollers out there this may be the utimate challange. I hope that someone in the next few years will carry this roll out, perhaps sooner... I really hope that it will be someone young! Come and beat us oldies! </p>
<p>I have tried the Reverse Sweep Elbow roll a couple of sessions and I'm not even close. This is a tough one but as I said - a challange. I really enjoy having a new goal, a new quest! </p>
<p>To be continued...</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Handcuff Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/handcuff-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/handcuff-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2025-02-21T14:07:39+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    What!? A new roll... on the competition list? Yes, this is a spoiler... well not for long. The Handcuff roll together with the Reverse Sweep Elbow roll is introduced to the Swedish Greenland Rolling competition in 2025. A rope loop is now part of your&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>What!? A new roll... on the competition list?</p>
<p>Yes, this is a spoiler... well not for long. The Handcuff roll together with the Reverse Sweep Elbow roll is introduced to the Swedish Greenland Rolling competition in 2025. </p>
<p>A rope loop is now part of your personal equipment (TBC, To be confirmed) and the diameter should be around 20cm (TBC). The roll is like a version of the Straight Jacket roll so basically everything from that post applies. <br>The new difficulty is that as I now have my hands behind my back, basically knuckle to knuckle, it is harder to "slide" up on the back deck than in the Straight Jacket. I have my arms in a better position so I can get "wide on the water" or at least wider... I need to arch my back a lot more than in the SJ so the "Camel" and "Cobra" pose will be used a lot during yoga practice. I started out holding my hands at my side, knuckles in. Then I moved the hands closer together behind my back until my fingertips touched. After that I thought I was home free - not so! It is harder than I thought to form fists or at least hold the rope loop as the final step. Now I haven't practiced more than one session but I would hold this roll almost, or as hard as the Straight Jacket roll. That may be revised but now I really feel my years and stiffness. </p>
<p>Update! Now I've had another session and found some tricks that work for me. The capsize can be slow if I do a "faceplant" with shoulders flat on the water. I find it hard to crunch with my hands on my back so I knife my shoulders until I reach the surface. I discovered that since my cockpit coaming is very far back my hands catch on it. In my qajaq I need to raise my hands rather high on my back to avoid getting stuck. When I got this worked out the Handcuff roll isn't that mysterious any more. Still not an easy one!</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="390" style="width: 700px; height: 390px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/T8Xvcb9jUHc" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Vad händer när jag beställer en kajak?</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/vad-haender-naer-jag-bestaeller-en-kajak.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/vad-haender-naer-jag-bestaeller-en-kajak.html</id>

        <updated>2025-04-28T20:01:14+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Lite mystiskt är det... hur kan Kajakskräddaren veta hur jag vill ha min kajak? Låt mig berätta vad som händer: 1. Vi pratas vid, telefon, chatt, Teams eller liknande, helst träffas vi. Jag vill veta vem du är, hur brukar du paddla/rolla, vad använder du&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Lite mystiskt är det... hur kan Kajakskräddaren veta hur jag vill ha min kajak?</p>
<p>Låt mig berätta vad som händer: </p>
<p>1. Vi pratas vid, telefon, chatt, Teams eller liknande, helst träffas vi. Jag vill veta vem du är, hur brukar du paddla/rolla, vad använder du idag (om något), vad vill du göra/utveckla i din nya kajak? Din kunskapsnivå avgör en del av designen. </p>
<p>2. Du får ange dina kroppsmått, som vikt, längd, avstånd mellan sittben och hälar etc. Du får en lista och lite bilder på hur du ska mäta. Eventuellt lägger jag upp den nedan. Här kommer en ny aspekt in, hur flexibel är du i kroppen? Vi kan ta den diskussionen privat men det ger vissa friheter om du är flexibel men det viktiga är att din kajak kommer att passa inte bara dina yttre kroppsmått utan hur du kan använda din kropp och kajak. Allt för att det ska bli DIN kajak. Naturligtvis kommer andra att kunna paddla den men det är DIG den är perfekt till. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/Maetbild_David.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="324" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/Maetbild_David-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>3. Jag börjar bygga, vill du så får du rapport från mig efter varje byggdag så du ser vad som händer och får se hur din kajak tar form. MEN, jag kan bara göra så mycket utan dig. </p>
<p>4. Provning! Jo, det är som hos skräddaren, du får komma och prova innan allt är klart. Om du vill virar vi in din kajak i plast så du kan prova den i vattnet också, då ser vi exakt hur många milimeter fribord du har och hur din kajak ligger i vattnet. <br>Vi ser till att fotstöd hamnar exakt, att lårstödet hamnar på rätt ställe över låren, att masik blir lagom hög så att den inte hindrar om du böjer dig fram, med mera. "Allt" går att ändra till dina önskemål i detta skede. Vill du så hjälper jag till med vad jag anser vara rätt för dig men det är du som bestämmer. <br>Rollare brukar avsluta provsittningen i poolen med en första roll. Det blir bara en eller ett par rollar då vi sällan har tuiliq på vid provsittning. </p>
<p>5. Jag bygger färdigt din kajak enligt det vi kommit överens om. Först skelettet och sedan klär jag den med ett nylontyg. Jag föredrar 240g per kvadratmeter i tygtjocklek men du kan få ett tjockare tyg på 460g per kvadratmeter. Skillnaden är mest känsla och kanske ett par hekto i vikt, det tjockare tyget absorberar mer lack också. Näst sista steg är lackning, här kan du få välja din egen färg! Jag använder pigment från Claessons Trätjära så allt de har kan du välja mellan. Detta är faktiskt ett av de tuffaste valen för de kunder jag haft... Jag väljer alltid en ljust brun till mig själv... fast jag kan kanske tänka om.</p>
<p>6. Kajaken är din! Vi är troligtvis goda vänner du och jag vid det här laget. Som du märker vill jag verkligen att det ska bli riktigt bra. Jag önskar att du ska få uppleva den glädjen och känslan som en Skräddarsydd kajak kan ge. Den blir verkligen personlig. Dessutom blir jag lycklig var gång jag lyfter upp min på biltaket! Cirka 11-12 kg brukar vikten sluta på. Små kajaker kan hamna lite lägre men det beror på det trä jag får tag på också. En turkajak kan bli 1-2 kg tyngre men 14 kg kajak är fortfarande en fröjd att lyfta upp på bilen. <br><br></p>
<p>Nedan är en Turkajak, inspirerad av Anas Acuta. Byggd till min fru...</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/IMG_20230507_122342.jpg" alt="" width="4000" height="1800" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/39/responsive/IMG_20230507_122342-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Kajakskräddaren</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/kajakskraeddaren.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/kajakskraeddaren.html</id>

        <updated>2025-05-25T14:02:55+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Vad är nu detta, Svenska!? Jo, jag bygger nu Skin on Frame kajaker till andra än mig själv! 😯 I och med att DU som kan tänkas vara intresserad troligen bor nära mig (Norden), så känner jag att det är mer personligt att skriva på&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Vad är nu detta, Svenska!?</p>
<p>Jo, jag bygger nu Skin on Frame kajaker till andra än mig själv! 😯 <br>I och med att DU som kan tänkas vara intresserad troligen bor nära mig (Norden), så känner jag att det är mer personligt att skriva på svenska. Hur går det till att beställa en kajak från mig? <a href="https://qajaqrolling.com/vad-haender-naer-jag-bestaeller-en-kajak.html">Kolla här!</a></p>
<p>Vill ni ha en tuiliq som passar till er qajaq så säljer jag RUGD tuiliqs! Riktigt bra kvalite, 3 mm neoprene, snörning runt ansiktet, elastiskt kardborreband kring handlederna. Endast svarta för tillfället. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/RUGD1.jpg" alt="" width="3840" height="2160" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/RUGD1-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>En Skin on Frame kajak är en traditionellt byggd kajak som de tillverkats under 100-tals kanske 1000-tals år på Grönland och i Arktis. Den består av ett skelett i trä som sedan kläs med duk, traditionellt sälskinn, som sedan görs vattentätt med lack, traditionellt användes fett och späck. En kajak som är byggd på detta sätt kan även betecknas Qajaq som är den Grönländska stavningen. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/DSC_0410.JPG" alt="" width="3840" height="2160" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-xs.JPG 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-sm.JPG 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-md.JPG 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/DSC_0410-2xl.JPG 1600w"></figure>
<p>Helst bygger jag dedikerade rollkajaker, det är jag bäst på, men om du vill ha en dagsturs- eller tur-kajak så går det också. Kajaken byggt till DIG, enligt dina kroppsmått och till dina önskemål.</p>
<p><strong>Rollkajak</strong>: På SM i Göteborg -24 var faktiskt ganska många av mina kajaker med även om de absolut flesta faktiskt var byggda för min kropp. Plats nummer 1, 2, 3 och 5 har kajaker som jag byggt. Det säger lite om hur bra det blir med en dedikerad rollkajak. Denna kajak är extremt liten volym i, vi strävar efter 15 mm fribord som är gränsen för tävling. Den är rak i köllinjen, platt i botten akteröver och lite mer V form föröver. Ett runt fördäck ger en snabb och lätt roll, ett platt och lågt och platt akterdäck utan ett irriterade ryggstöd som biter sig in i korsryggen ger dig en möjlighet att lyckas med till och med en Straight Jacket roll. Med bredd och höjd för lårstöden som anpassas på millimetern till din kropp och stil får du en kajak som inte kommer att sätta några begränsningar. </p>
<p><strong>Dagstur: </strong>Liknar rollkajaken till stora delar med nu ökar vi på volymen lite så vi inte får in vatten i vågorna. Nu får du även möjlighet att ta med dig lite matsäck och annan packning. En lite bekvämare kajak men du väljer om du vill låta den gå åt roll- eller tur- hållet.</p>
<p><strong>Turkajak: </strong> Vill du ha en kajak som är mer åt det "vanliga" hållet som är en Skin on Frame variant av till exempel en Anas Acuta (Valley) eller liknande så bygger jag gärna en sådan. Turkajaker utrustas gärna med vattentäta påsar (stora avlånga) som fyller upp utrymmet framför fotstöden och akter om ryggen för säkerhet och packmöjligheter. Man kan också använda en så kallad "SeaSock" som är som en mjuk sittbrunn. <br>Ska du på veckolång tur? Kontakta Kajakkspesialistens Anders Thygessen och be honom bygga en Baidarka.</p>
<p>Jag gör även grönlandspaddlar - hela eller delbara, norsaq och harpuner (med norsaq). </p>
<p>Är du intresserad så kontakta mig på: </p>
<p><a href="mailto:david.o.tang@gmail.com">david.o.tang@gmail.com </a></p>
<p>så kan vi prata vidare.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/David-Saekerhet-1280-720.jpg" alt="" width="505" height="284" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/David-Saekerhet-1280-720-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h2>Fjärde leveransen från Kajakskräddaren! </h2>
<p>Även denna Qajaq kommer att få bo i Danmark, har den starka Danska kronan med saken att göra??? En utpräglad rollqajaq som Frank ska ha för att utmana Jakob (D13) i de Danska Mästerskapen i Grönlandsroll. Jag blev lite överraskad när färgen bestämdes snabbt och bestämt till orange! Det blev ju så snyggt! Mycket positiv till denna nyansen! Linjerna blev också som jag hade visualiserat så jag hoppas att den rollar som Frank vill att den ska rolla. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250510_114331.jpg" alt="" width="4000" height="1800" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114331-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250510_114500.jpg" alt="" width="4000" height="1800" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250510_114500-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h2>Tredje leveransen från Kajakskräddaren! </h2>
<p>D-15 numera döpt till Måsart (eller Mozart) blev en utmaning. En dedikerad rollkajak till en lätt person!!! Den är den lägsta, minst från köl till relingen, som jag någonsin byggt. 11 cm i totaldjup om jag minns rätt! Mät upp 11 cm och se efter, det är väldigt lite volym. Mönster och färgvalet - oj! En hel del prat och diskussioner, sedan fick jag bestämma själv. Jag gjorde mitt bästa, kanske skulle jag låtit kunden komma och lacka den själv...</p>
<p>Den är mycket omtyckt vad jag har förstått och jag har fått en ny vän! <figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/Masart4.jpeg" alt="" width="2048" height="1312" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-md.jpeg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-lg.jpeg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-xl.jpeg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart4-2xl.jpeg 1600w"></figure>
<h2><figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/Masart2.jpeg" alt="" width="254" height="565" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-md.jpeg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-lg.jpeg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-xl.jpeg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart2-2xl.jpeg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/Masart6-2.jpeg" alt="" width="442" height="199" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-md.jpeg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-lg.jpeg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-xl.jpeg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/Masart6-2-2xl.jpeg 1600w"></figure></h2>
<h2>Andra leveransen från Kajakskräddaren!</h2>
<p>D-14 (Dagstur - Roll) togs emot den 29 december 2024. Som jag uppfattade det var kajaken mycket efterlängtad och älskad redan vid leverans. 😍 Detta var ett special upplägg där det ingick extra allt! Pulley system för att få in packning eller flytkroppar i fören och aktern, skedda som är avtagbar, en paddel nummer 45 samt instruktion för att göra en handroll. Handrollen satt 3-4 gånger på var sida under lektionen, får se om den sitter... Det var ett känslofyllt möte och avsked, D-14 är vacker och inte bara en rollkajak. D-14 har en design för att både rolla utmärkt samt vara bekväm på dagsturer. Jag hoppas att ni kommer finna mycket glädje tillsammans. Färgen är en utblandad Milori-blå.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal); outline: 3px solid rgba(var(--color-primary-rgb), 0.55) !important;" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250207_145711.jpg" alt="" width="192" height="426" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145711-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal); outline: 3px solid rgba(var(--color-primary-rgb), 0.55) !important;" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20241229_144927.jpg" alt="" width="191" height="425" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20241229_144927-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);" src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/IMG_20250207_145807.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="225" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/IMG_20250207_145807-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h2>Första leveransen från Kajakskräddaren!</h2>
<p>D-13 (Rollkajak) togs emot av sin beställare fredagen den 13 December 2024. Jag är säker på att kajaken kommer att få ett bra hem hos den tvåfaldige Danske Mästaren! Den provrollades på Kungsbackafjorden under dagen och de båda verkar komma mycket bra överens. Ryktet säger att Straight Jacket rollen är nära nu...</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2.jpg" alt="" width="180" height="400" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/38/responsive/D13-och-Jakob-Bisgaard-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Skin on Frame Material</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/skin-on-frame-material.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/skin-on-frame-material.html</id>

        <updated>2023-12-26T15:07:58+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I've been asked several times where to get material for a Skin on Frame SoF build in Sweden or northen Europe. Here is a list of my suppliers which I hope will be useful for You as well. Lumber: I go to my local lumberstore&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I've been asked several times where to get material for a Skin on Frame SoF build in Sweden or northen Europe. Here is a list of my suppliers which I hope will be useful for You as well. </p>
<p>Lumber: I go to my local lumberstore for all straight lumber. I spend time to select the best Spruce lumber I can find. My suggestion is to buy a bit larger dimensions than you need and cut around the worst knots, also to laminate the gunwales to avoid weak areas. Byggmax is my store in Kungsbacka. </p>
<p>Bending stock: I haven't found "green" or freshly cut bending stock yet but I keep looking. In the meantime I buy Ash planks from <a href="https://abitra.se/produkt/planhyvlat-ovriga-traslag/">Abi Trä in Frölunda (Gothenburg)</a>. Same procedure here to find straight grain planks and so far the material I've got is very good. Last build (number 10) I didn't break any ribs but usually up to a third of the ribs break. </p>
<p>Cloth: The best cloth I've found is excellent! Provided by Marcin Bober in Poland. Marcin hasn't set up a website yet but is very professional in everything he delivers. His english is understandable albeit not perfect but don't let that discourage you. Also don't be alarmed as you may be asked to use his wifes PayPal account, <a href="https://www.mimisoapery.com/en/">Mimi's Soapery.</a> Among other things Marcin provides Nylon cloth of two thicknesses, 260 grams per square meter and 430 grams per square meter. I've used both and I'm very happy with it. To get in contact with Marcin check Facebook or write me and I'll set you up.  </p>
<p>Thread/Artificial Sinew: Same supplier as above Marcin Bober! Ask for your specific colour, you may be in luck. </p>
<p>PU varnish: Same supplier as above for 2-part PU, Marcin Bober! Works great! I sometimes use Coelan 1-part PU which I like even better as I don't have to mix it and it handles great. It cost about 3-4 times as much as Marcin's PU so it is very doubtful if it is worth it. I get Coelan from <a href="https://www.toplicht.de/en/paint-boatbuilding/paint-conservation/coelan-coating/3150/coelan-boat-coating-transparent-gloss-finish?number=2621-075">Toplicht in Hamburg.</a> Three cans of 750 ml is sufficient. </p>
<p>Leather cord: I love to use the traditional deck riggings using leather cords and sliders. I buy round english leather cord from <a href="https://www.tjaderlader.se/rundrem-natur-vegetabilgarvad-engelska">Tjäderläder</a>. 5 mm for the rigging front and aft of the cockpit and 7 mm for loops front and aft to stick your paddle into. 5 m of 5 mm and 0,5-1 m of 7mm cord. They may not be the cheapest but the best I've found. Sorry to say but I don't think they have a webpage in english, send me a mail if you need help.</p>
<p>Pigments: I use pigment in the second layer of varnish to "dye" my qajaqs. As the pigment is basically crushed stone it doesn't fade and is in itself an UV protection. My local supplier is <a href="https://claessons.com/pigment/">Claessons Trätjära</a> at Ringön, Gothenburg. They also have the best linseed oil! The colours are of course limited but you can always mix them. In stock they have multiple variations of: White, Red, Yellow, Terra (brown), Umbra (brown), Green, Blue, and Black. </p>
<p>If I can do anything to help or assist you in your build, don't hesitate to contact me at <a href="mailto:david.o.tang@gmail.com">david.o.tang@gmail.com</a> or via Facebook, Messenger, Instagram etc. </p>
<p>Note: I don't get any benefits from the companies mentioned above. I have been searching for suppliers in my region of the world for 5-6 years and this is the current list. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Useful links</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/useful-links.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/useful-links.html</id>

        <updated>2023-12-26T15:12:28+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    As always, a lot of people have done a lot of work a lot better than I could ever do. To start with; how do you get your first roll. I don't intend to teach the first roll as others can do that better. Perhaps&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>As always, a lot of people have done a lot of work a lot better than I could ever do. </p>
<p>To start with; how do you get your first roll. I don't intend to teach the first roll as others can do that better. Perhaps I can help in person, but that's off the scope for the webpage. My recommendation is to find professional rolling teachers locally. If they are hard to find then get the DVD:</p>
<p><a href="https://kayakways.net/videos/digital-downloads/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"This is the Roll" by Cheri Perry and Turner Wilson of Kayakways</a>.</p>
<p>You can find it as a Disc as well on their site: <a href="http://www.kayakways.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.kayakways.net</a></p>
<p>Excellent instructions and animations on Eiichi Eto's page <a href="http://www.storm-on.com/">Storm On</a></p>
<p>Paddlegear at <a href="https://www.chillcheater.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reed Chillcheater</a></p>
<p>Greenland paddles at <a href="https://gramkajak.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gram Kayak</a></p>
<p>Skin on Frame, Norwegian Wood paddles and more with Anders Thygesen at <a href="https://www.yourvismawebsite.com/kajakkspesialisten-as-1/lang-EN" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kajakkspesialisten</a><br>Note that Anders sells Brooks Tuiliqs! </p>
<p>My club "<a href="www.rolltokarna.se">The Rolling Lunatics" or "Rolltokarna</a>" <figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/Rolltokarnalogga.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="295" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-xs.jpg 300w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-sm.jpg 480w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-md.jpg 768w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://qajaqrolling.com/media/posts/36/responsive/Rolltokarnalogga-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>34 Paddling Upside Down</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/34-paddling-upside-down.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/34-paddling-upside-down.html</id>

        <updated>2024-04-04T12:02:54+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This manoeuvre is pretty straight forward. I put my paddle under the qajaq, capsize and go. Now there are a few hint to be able to go far... First of all - go straight! The points awarded are calculated from the straight line and I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OTCWnZb-3dY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>This manoeuvre is pretty straight forward. I put my paddle under the qajaq, capsize and go. Now there are a few hint to be able to go far...</p>
<p>First of all - go straight! The points awarded are calculated from the straight line and I normally have to paddle next to a line in the water with distance markings. If the water is clear it can be possible to see the line and adjust my path to it. I get 1 point for the first 3 meters and 1 additional point for every two meters after that. 5 meters is 2 points, so is 6 meters. </p>
<p>I have seen paddlers rocking the qajaq to get the paddle deeper in the water as in a sprint stroke. That is a good idea both for power and for going straight.</p>
<p>To get a low profile under water is beneficial, lower drag, longer distance. I try to have my nose on the deck but it's hard. Hard to see where I'm going and hard because I compress my lungs. </p>
<p>The most important aspect of this manoeuvre is to hold my breath for a looooong time. I have got some help from free divers. When I practice I rarely measure my distance, more counting the seconds or strokes I make. Counting strokes are easier, seconds have a tendency for me to speed up as I get a bit stressed under water. </p>
<p>Practice paddling upside down! There are a lot of points go gain and it's not very difficult. It can be worth as much as a Straight Jacket Roll... (23 meters = 11 points)</p>
<p>Judges note: The distance is measured along the straight marked line. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>33 Straight Jacket Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/33-straight-jacket-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2024-04-04T12:01:37+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I have finally made it. With the excellent help and instructions of Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and Jörgen Fagereng Wessel! Thank you! This is an excellent example of how hands on instruction is invaluable to written instructions. I posted the instructions I got from Anne-Sofie and Jörgen&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mPk2acArQCs?si=Y4M_DS8azyKkx27G" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>I have finally made it. With the excellent help and instructions of Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and Jörgen Fagereng Wessel! Thank you! This is an excellent example of how hands on instruction is invaluable to written instructions. I posted the instructions I got from Anne-Sofie and Jörgen earlier this spring but couldn't make out what I really needed to do. I invited them to come from Norway, they did and they taught me. </p>
<p>This is what I can tell you about my journey so far.</p>
<p>Prerequisites: <br>- A strong will to succeed, the process can be a bit painful at times. <br>- A qajaq that fits you, low back deck, full contact with your thighs. <br>- Good twist in your torso.<br>- An understanding of what supports you; water, shoulders, secondary stability, weight distribution inside and out. <br>- You should be able to do an Elbow roll with some ease, double elbow as well. If not start there. </p>
<p>Yoga and stretching. YES! For me this is somewhat painful but makes all the difference. And it takes time so don't set a timetable, do what you can and things will come to you. </p>
<p>Qajaq: This is one of the reasons I got into SOF qajaq building, so I can build myself a qajaq which allows me to do a SJ roll. Not that the qajaq does anything for you but some attributes need to be fulfilled. My current one (T2D5 - TvångsTröja David #5 or Strait Jacket David #5) is great, built for this purpose alone. There are two issues with it, the masik is a tad too high and it's black, l loved my brown ones. The R2D4 (Rockhopping and Roll David#4) had a masik slightly lower and I had to push my knees under it, so I raised it 1 cm for T2D5 and now I regret it a bit. When I lean forward my arms touch the masik stopping me from getting low on the foredeck. This isn't a problem in forward finishing rolls since my arms are not in the way but.... <br>Padding and a snug fit is vital for this roll. Both at the masik and at the hips. If your hips slide down in the qajaq to the water gunwale it's very hard to get past the secondary stability and on to the back deck. I have now padded my hips as much as I can without restricting butt/hip movement. </p>
<p>The main things I work on at the moment are:<br>Getting my shoulders flat and parallel to the surface as I reach up towards the sky before I start the backward sweep.</p>
<p>As I get to the static brace position I push my head back and try to keep my shoulders flat. I can now stay in the static brace - straight jacket style - if my timing is a bit off and I can't recover in one motion. It's clear to me now that timing is important but not crucial.<br><br>To recover to the back deck I need to ease up with my lower back first, then chest and head out of the water last. This is what Anne-Sofie and Jörgen wrote to me and later showed in detail. </p>
<h3>Additional sources: </h3>
<p>I also got this answer from Anne-Sofie Furuhaug and Jörgen Fagereng Wessel on Facebook:</p>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>Straitjacket roll learning process:</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>I assume you already know the hand and elbow rolls.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>I split most back ending rolls in two parts:</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>1) the capsized to balance brace and</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>2) balance brace to back deck.</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>For the straitjacket roll getting the first part is a matter of timing, strong hip/knee drive and sufficient twisting of upper body. The second part is what most people seem to struggle with. If you manage to use the momentum from the first part that is great, but I found that it was easier to simply learn it from balance brace.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>Again, good twist of upper body is important, so is backward flexibility (practice the cobra stance in yoga).</em></div>
<div dir="auto"><em>I practiced a lot of balance bracing! Then it was beginning to go from balance brace to back deck with hands folded, and repeating while gradually moving the hands closer to the correct straitjacket position. In the beginning I found it helps moving my sea leg over to the other side in the kayak (every bit helps).</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>The kayak matters a lot, so does padding and fitting. I can not do the straitjacket roll in many kayaks, and I have some padding under front of the kayak (like a padded masik) and some at the hips to keep me from slipping too far to one side of the kayak. If it is too tight it limits my movement and twisting.</em></div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"><em>It is important to try to use the lower back muscles to try to get the lower back up on the back deck, not just the upper torso and head.</em></div>
</div>
<h3>I found this on Helen Wilsons site <a href="http://www.greenlandorbust.org">www.greenlandorbust.org</a></h3>
<p><em>Often when first attempting the Straitjacket Roll, the paddler tries to “sweep” onto the back deck, and essentially bumps into it. They can hang out there all day (breathing), but not actually get onto the deck. Does this sound familiar? In this description, the “sweep” is the problem. This “sweep” usually works with a hand roll, fist roll, brick roll and sometimes even the Elbow Roll, but it will not work with the Straightjacket Roll. For the Straightjacket Roll, you need to think of your upper body as a lever, and instead of trying to “sweep” onto the back deck, push your upper body toward the ground, which will give you the leverage to fully recover. Following are the steps to a successful Straightjacket Roll (described with a right-side recovery):</em></p>
<p><em>– Place your arms against your chest with your fingers and thumbs under your armpits.</em></p>
<p><em>– Capsize to the left with your shoulders parallel to the side of the kayak and your forehead down (this will give you a rounded spine).</em></p>
<p><em>– RELAX until your body gets to the highest position possible on the right side of the kayak (your shoulders should be parallel to the surface).</em></p>
<p><em>– Throw your upper body toward the ground, using your back as a lever and keeping your shoulders parallel to the surface. Simultaneously, drive hard with the right knee.</em></p>
<p><em>– Slide up onto the back deck (your head may hit the side of the kayak during the recovery).</em></p>
<p><em>– Helen</em></p>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s">
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">Two pros giving their thoughts. I sincerely thank you both. </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">Judges note<br>Your forearms shall be pressed against your body throughout the roll and your fingers shall remain in your armpits. </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">Earlier attempts for reference:</div>
<div dir="auto"><iframe width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F5fdRcgUtMY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TfeMOI9bHvQ" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div>
</div>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>32 Elbow Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/32-elbow-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/32-elbow-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2024-04-04T11:54:06+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The elbow roll is quite a bit more difficult than the previous lay back rolls. Not as hard as the forward finishing clenched fist and brick rolls but still. Have a look at the preparations working up to the Brick roll Layback - they are&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="393" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WV8S09qxpSw" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The elbow roll is quite a bit more difficult than the previous lay back rolls. Not as hard as the forward finishing clenched fist and brick rolls but still. </p>
<p>Have a look at the preparations working up to the Brick roll Layback - they are the same as to the elbow roll and then some. </p>
<p>When I started trying the elbow roll I was amazed at how much lift I do get using my hand or fist. Not only is that lift gone in the elbow roll but there is a another more subtle difficulty. As I put my hand on the back of my head it is much harder for me to arch back. This is mostly a mental thing but also a bit of flexibility of the shoulder. When I try arching my head back in this position my elbow like to come forward. This means that I need to actively push my elbow out and down during the little sweep I get. Don't get me wrong, I don't mean to push the elbow down for support like I can get from a paddle, just push it out so it lays parallel to the surface and don't point to the sky. If you push it down for support it will sink and our shoulders will knife. </p>
<p>My arching is more pronounced and I use both my legs to turn the qajaq. I've mentioned it several times before and I have a different feeling when using both legs in lay back versus forward finishing rolls. In lay back rolls I try to push my non-water leg out, like out to the gunwhale, in forward finishing rolls I push it down, like to the bottom of the qajaq. I've found it easier to push the non-water leg out in lay back rolls as I can arch my back more, or at least it feels easier. In forward finishing i crunch my abs in this position and pushing the non-water leg down is ok. I find more momentum with my legs pushing down if the timing is right. </p>
<p>As in all rolls, don't raise your head out of the water until last. I have good momentum in the roll in the video so I get away with it. </p>
<p>Strangely enough I set up very differently in the elbow roll than in all the other lay back rolls. I twist my torso so I face sideways, point the elbow forward and capsize. It feels like doing a face-plant into the water. Most people try to lean forward close to the fore deck and I guess that's fine but it doesn't work for me. </p>
<p>Lastly, hold your position - facing sideways or forward until your nose get very close to the surface before you un-tuck and sweep your torso. </p>
<p>Judges note: The hand shall stay on the back of your head throughout the whole roll. It is ok to use the other arm as counterweight. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
