<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Qajaq Rolling</title>
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com" />
    <updated>2023-03-17T12:20:48+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>David Täng</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://qajaqrolling.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>17 Successive Storm Rolls</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/17-successive-storm-rolls.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/17-successive-storm-rolls.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-17T12:20:48+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Now this is a set of rolls what can be easy if I only set out to do 3 in 10 seconds or madly difficult if I go for 6. With simply doing my normal&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="696" height="390" style="width: 696px; height: 390px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sGMqmb1tt-I" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Now this is a set of rolls what can be easy if I only set out to do 3 in 10 seconds or madly difficult if I go for 6. </p>
<p>With simply doing my normal Storm roll over and over I can possibly manage 3 or 4 in 10 seconds. To do more than that takes practice and some know-how. I got my first introduction at the workshop after the Danish Greenland Rolling Championships in 2022. The winner of the men Championship Noud Jentink from the Netherlands showed and instructed willingly - Thank you Noud! And thank you for your knowledge in the Straight Jacket roll! </p>
<p>You can see the basics of the technique in the video above. First roll is (for me) just the standard setup, but then it becomes more interesting. The "back" of the paddle slices into the water to about vertical, then the angle change so I get a pull of the paddle as it slices up to the surface on the new side. Once the paddle reaches the surface, the motion reverses and the angle is changed 90 degrees. It is almost like a scull and it feels like a zig-zag motion. I work on the technique in a slow pace and if I get the rythm I try to speed up. The motion is rather fluid in the video but the pace is slow. </p>
<p>In competition the time start when my head touches the water and the roll is considered done (awarded points) then my head is out of the water. Minimum to be awarded any points is three, and one point per roll so I can get three to six points per side. That is a lot of points to be gained so I suggest we all start practising. I say six points which is my goal but there is no limit, only the 10 seconds. </p>
<p>Judges note:<br>There is no penalty if rolls are preformed after the 10 seconds has passed. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>16 Sculling with the Paddle held Under the Kayak</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/16-sculling-with-the-paddle-held-under-the-kayak.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/16-sculling-with-the-paddle-held-under-the-kayak.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-17T11:30:52+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Of the sculling rolls going all the way around I think this is the easiest. I got a very low volume qajaq so I can easily reach around and then it helps me to tuck&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="697" height="391" style="width: 697px; height: 391px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Oc3IWZ6BQVU" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Of the sculling rolls going all the way around I think this is the easiest. I got a very low volume qajaq so I can easily reach around and then it helps me to tuck low over the foredeck. There isn't much to tell which is new to this roll, If you can do the sculling over the foredeck this is the same, just remember to push with your leading hand and have a wide stroke and an aggressive blade angle. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>15 Roll with Arms Crossed</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/15-roll-with-arms-crossed.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/15-roll-with-arms-crossed.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-16T11:54:17+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The Roll with Arms Crossed is basically the same as a Storm roll. With the arms crossed I can't lean forward as much and it is difficult to get a good sweep. When I first&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="696" height="390" style="width: 696px; height: 390px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lj-FBzyGHCI" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The Roll with Arms Crossed is basically the same as a Storm roll. With the arms crossed I can't lean forward as much and it is difficult to get a good sweep. When I first tried this roll I only used a pry to recover, now I work to get more of a sweep. </p>
<p>There are two ways to set up, with the hand towards the bow on top or under the aft arm/hand. Some judges require the bow hand to be under the aft hand as this is quite a bit harder. I do the harder variant as the first roll in the video above and the easier one after that. I think you can see the more upright roll first as the arms locks me in that position. It is good standard to hold up my hands after the finished roll to show the judge that the arms are indeed crossed. </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>14 Sculling Roll with Paddle held above Isserfik</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/14-sculling-roll-with-paddle-held-above-isserfik.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/14-sculling-roll-with-paddle-held-above-isserfik.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-16T11:17:28+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The Sculling Roll with Paddle held above Isserfik or "backrest" is the hardest sculling roll for me. I find it hard to bend forward when my hands are behind me in strange angles and it's&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="700" height="391" style="width: 700px; height: 391px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Amh1pk7iwDE" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The Sculling Roll with Paddle held above Isserfik or "backrest" is the hardest sculling roll for me. I find it hard to bend forward when my hands are behind me in strange angles and it's easy to engage the wrong leg. </p>
<p>The detail I spend most time on is how to hold the paddle. WHAT?  YES!  I don't get the full power of the sculling in this position so I really need to have all the power I can get in both sculling directions. If my hands are positioned for a powerful forward scull, the backward scull seems to be more of a "transport of the paddle" stroke. I have found that I hold the paddle best if the edge of the blade comes all the way in between my thumb and first finger. My friend holds it in a different way so you try it out for yourself. </p>
<p>In all three of the sculling rolls what go all the way around I push with the leading hand and try to hold the trailing hand in a fixed position. When I started practice I pulled with both hands to no use and broke a couple of paddles in the process, they make nice norsaqs. </p>
<p>Judges note:<br>Have to scull the way around, not just one sweep. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>13 Sculling with Paddle held Horizontal on Foredeck</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/13-sculling-with-paddle-held-horizontal-on-foredeck.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/13-sculling-with-paddle-held-horizontal-on-foredeck.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-16T10:26:30+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is in my opinion the first real sculling roll. Some say that you should progress to this roll by sculling at the end of a Storm roll. I never found that to be the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CkASckaLDOM" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>This is in my opinion the first <strong>real</strong> sculling roll. <br>Some say that you should progress to this roll by sculling at the end of a Storm roll. I never found that to be the same movements or feeling so that doesn't help me. In the worst case I ruin a powerful Storm roll. I did try a lot of different ways to practice this roll but in the end I found that what I need is a powerful scull and not much more. As previously stated: Sculling is Sculling is Sculling (-Turner Wilson).</p>
<p>My path to the Sculling with the paddle held horizontal on foredeck went through Chest Sculling and then simply by doing the full Sculling roll. I remember the first time I got this roll - I was so surprised that it was so easy! And then I couldn't do it again for weeks... As I practice my Chest sculling I notice that the speed of the paddle through the water is quite slow to get a powerful scull. I also notice that the blade angle is much more aggressive than during a sweep. As I had only done successful sweeps previously this is a game changer. To get a good scull in one direction is ok, but to have it both ways is the trick. This requires a big change in the blade angle, about 90 degrees. If I go too fast or have narrow sculls I don't get the benefit of the great power a good scull can produce.</p>
<p>To get full points I need to scull at least 4-5 times and keep the paddle as perpendicular to the qajaq as possible. </p>
<p>Judges note:<br> The paddle shall be held close to perpendicular on the deck of the qajaq.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>12 Vertical Sculling Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/12-vertical-sculling-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/12-vertical-sculling-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-16T10:08:31+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Vertical sculling roll is the easiest of the sculling rolls according to me. As I discussed in the post for chest sculling most people don't scull at first when they lay on the belly, just&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="696" height="390" style="width: 696px; height: 390px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jbnQlSD6Huc" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Vertical sculling roll is the easiest of the sculling rolls according to me. As I discussed in the post for chest sculling most people don't scull at first when they lay on the belly, just pry. When I realised that I did just that, pry while I should be chest sculling I went back and started over. That helped me to develop a powerful scull, and frankly sculling is sculling as Turner Wilson stated. Sculling is a bit different from sweeping back and forth, I go a bit faster and use a lot more blade angle. When I fail it is almost always the same mistake, too fast, not wide enough and not aggressive enough blade angle. It is a bit hard to practice but chest sculling and then vertical sculling "roll" is my way to go. </p>
<p>There are some variations to this roll so be sure to check and double check the rules in your country! <br>First variation is to actually roll all the way. This is a bit easier but also more disorientating. I can use the momentum of the capsize to get up on the other side. I personally haven't practised this very much and I have problems twisting the paddle to come into the sculling/recovery position.  <br>Second is how to hold your hands. Palms in or palms out. Cheri and Turner teach palms out in their amazing video "This is the Roll 2" so that was the way I first learned. It makes for a rather smooth forward finish recovery. If I hold my palms out the starting position feels very familiar and is a draw stroke or bow rudder or sculling for going sideways. The sculling also feels more powerful, but forward recovery is difficult so I tend to come up almost straight. I don't think the palm in our out makes much difference to how hard the roll is so practice both if your rules don't state exactly how to score. </p>
<p>Judges note: (Swedish rules!)<br>Up and down on the same side. Palms in or out doesn't matter but the paddle can not deviate from vertical more than normal wiggle. </p>
<p><br><em>(Another rule set: Palms out at setup, palms in at recovery. 360 degree roll, capsize on one side and recover on the other.)</em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>11 Shotgun Roll</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/11-shotgun-roll.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/11-shotgun-roll.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-10T10:47:48+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The Shotgun or Armpit roll is one of the easiest on the Greenland Rolling Competition list. It's basically a Standard Greenland roll with an extremely extended paddle. This also means that I can get a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="697" height="391" style="width: 697px; height: 391px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bK-BwDmJnPY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The Shotgun or Armpit roll is one of the easiest on the Greenland Rolling Competition list. It's basically a Standard Greenland roll with an extremely extended paddle. This also means that I can get a lot of lift from the paddle and it may "jump out of position" during the roll. So take it easy, no rush! I make a smooth sweep with the paddle out to perpendicular to the qajaq and use the off hand as a counterweight. I need to return to the setup position in this roll to get full points. </p>
<p>Judges note:<br>The paddle shall be held against the shoulder, not in the armpit. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>10 Reverse Sweep with paddle held behind head</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/10-reverse-sweep-with-paddle-held-behind-head.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/10-reverse-sweep-with-paddle-held-behind-head.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-10T10:39:59+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The Reverse Sweep with the paddle held behind head isn't as hard on the joints as some of the other strange looking rolls. It is hard to move in this position so I have found&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="699" height="392" style="width: 699px; height: 392px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vFLlai7PF5w" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The Reverse Sweep with the paddle held behind head isn't as hard on the joints as some of the other strange looking rolls. It is hard to move in this position so I have found two things important to complete this roll. </p>
<p>First to have control over my head and thereby the blade angle during the sweep. I have a tendency to bow down into the water early in reverse sweep rolls and if I do that here the blade angle will make the paddle dive. So keep your head up until the end of the sweep. </p>
<p>Second; I find a pry at the end helpful and the pry in this roll goes the "wrong" way, I push the paddle out, away from the qajaq. That is why do not place the end of the blade on the neck in the setup. See, I got 50 cm or so to pry with if I need it as I do in the second/outdoor roll in the video above.</p>
<p>As the body position is very strange in this roll (as well) I sometimes use the non-water leg instead of the water leg to raise and then the roll becomes a muscle struggle and usually fail. <br>When everything falls into place the roll is quite easy as the paddle gives you tremendous power to get up. </p>
<p>Judges note:<br>It's ok to take your time capsizing. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>9 Standard Roll with paddle held behind head</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/9-standard-roll-with-paddle-held-behind-head.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/9-standard-roll-with-paddle-held-behind-head.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-09T12:20:30+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This roll require some flexibility. My problem is to lean forward in this strange setup position. As you see in the video above when I'm outdoors in the ice and snow and dressed appropriately I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="694" height="389" style="width: 694px; height: 389px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9ujDsGlBSjs" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>This roll require some flexibility. My problem is to lean forward in this strange setup position. As you see in the video above when I'm outdoors in the ice and snow and dressed appropriately I have difficulties capsizing. </p>
<p>I know that I can "swing" the paddle over the front of the qajaq to capsize but I try to setup in a static way, looks nicer. <br>I have to really wait this one out, to float up to the surface on the new side before starting the sweep. If I start too early the paddle will go straight down. I can arch my back in the sweep but not press my head back since the paddle angle is controlled by the neck the paddle will sink if I do. </p>
<p>I believe that you will have to return to the setup position to get points. </p>
<p>Judges notes: <br>It is not required to have the paddle in contact with the gunwale at setup.  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>8 Reverse Sweep with paddle held behind back.</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Täng</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://qajaqrolling.com/8-reverse-sweep-with-paddle-held-behind-back.html"/>
        <id>https://qajaqrolling.com/8-reverse-sweep-with-paddle-held-behind-back.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-07T11:48:51+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is a roll that makes me dizzy just thinking about it. Once I got used to the reverse sweep and the disorientation it provokes and now this. I felt like I was trapped in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="631" height="354" style="width: 631px; height: 354px;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YgmzzdL3hgY" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>This is a roll that makes me dizzy just thinking about it. Once I got used to the reverse sweep and the disorientation it provokes and now this. I felt like I was trapped in a strange bodylock the first times I tried it, I couldn't move. I had friends looking and standing in the water next to me but since they couldn't do the roll either it wasn't much help. </p>
<p>First of all, warm up thoroughly! This roll isn't quite as bad on my joints as the Spine Roll but still... </p>
<p>To succeed I try to get the paddle on top of the qajaq so the tip can come closer to the surface. Otherwise the sweep simply goes straight down towards the bottom of the ocean/pool. For me it's hard to lean forward as much as I would like when my hands are behind me but I try. The motion is the same as in the standard RS but still it feels awkward. I try to sweep all the way so the tip of the paddle hits the side of the qajaq way in front. To do this I let my aft hand go around my back all the way. I also struggled as I was using the wrong leg, yes this roll takes out the worst in me. I also work on the blade angle, it needs to be a bit more aggressive than normal to give me more power. <br>Besides all that it's quite a fun roll! </p>
<p>Judges note: <br>Need to be completed with the body leaning forward. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
